<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="UVA" rend="none"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="none"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOdia SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-dia.ent"> %ISOdia;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-tech.ent"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="UVA" rend="none">
<teiHeader type="migrated">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Cochrane_Peerless Women</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl/></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="paragraph_function">
                <category id="setting">
                    <catDesc>Specifying time and or place.</catDesc>
                    <category id="orientation">
                        <catDesc>Signifying audience proximity or distance from setting.</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </category>
                <category id="home">
                    <catDesc>Description of home.</catDesc>
                    <category id="home_childhood">
                        <catDesc>Description of childhood home.</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category id="home_adulthood">
                        <catDesc>Description of person's later home(s).</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category id="characteristics_protagonist">
                        <catDesc></catDesc>
                    </category>
                    
                    
                    
                </category>
                
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="paragraph_type">
    <category id="beginning">
        <catDesc>Introducing narrative.</catDesc>
        <category id="beginning_protagonist">
            <catDesc>Bio begins with subject of biography.</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category id="beginning_family">
            <catDesc>Bio begins with reference to relatives.</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category id="beginning_historical">
            <catDesc>Bio begins with reference to era, not persons.</catDesc>
        </category>
        
        
        
    </category>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
                <category id="person">
                    <catDesc>Any actual human being specified in narrative.</catDesc>
                    <category id="person_family">
                        <catDesc>Family member by name or role.</catDesc>
                        <category id="father">
                            <catDesc>Protagonist's father.</catDesc>
                        </category>
                        <category id="mother">
                            <catDesc>Protagonist's mother.</catDesc>
                        </category>
                        <category id="brother">
                            <catDesc>Protagonist's brother or brothers.</catDesc>
                        </category>
                        <category id="sister">
                            <catDesc>Protagonist's sister or sisters.</catDesc>
                        </category>
                        <category id="partner">
                            <catDesc>Husband or life companion.</catDesc>
                        </category>
                        <category id="child">
                            <catDesc>Child or children of protagonist.</catDesc>
                        </category>
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                    </category>
                    <category id="person_nonfamily">
                        <catDesc>Specific non-relatives.</catDesc>
                        <category id="intimate">
                            <catDesc>Non-relatives who are close to protagonist.</catDesc>
                            <category id="lover">
                                <catDesc>Person loved by or who loves protagonist.</catDesc>
                            </category>
                            <category id="suitor">
                                <catDesc>Person who seeks marriage with protagonist.</catDesc>
                            </category>
                            <category id="fiance">
                                <catDesc>Person who is engaged to marry protagonist.</catDesc>
                            </category>
                            <category id="protege">
                                <catDesc>A non-family non-sexual intimate of less power e.g. foster child or favorite assistant.</catDesc>
                            </category>
                           <category id="friend">
                               <catDesc>Non-family non-sexual intimate peer</catDesc>
                           </category>
                            
                            
                            
                            
                        </category>
                        <category id="associate">
                            <catDesc>Non-family non-intimate adult persons who work with or frequently associate with protagonist.</catDesc>
                            <category id="peer">
                                <catDesc>Associates of equal status (class, occupation, power) to protagonist</catDesc>
                                <category id="female_peer">
                                    <catDesc>female associates of equal status (class, occupation, power) to protagonist</catDesc>
                                </category>
                                <category id="male_peer">
                                    <catDesc>male associates of equal status (class, occupation, power) to protagonist</catDesc>
                                </category>
                            </category>
                            <category id="subordinate">
                                <catDesc>Associates of lesser status, dependents, assistants</catDesc>
                                <category id="female_subordinate">
                                    <catDesc>Female subordinate associates.</catDesc>
                                    <category id="girl">
                                        <catDesc>Associate female children of any class.</catDesc>
                                    </category>
                                    
                                </category>
                                </category>
                                <category id="male_subordinate">
                                    <catDesc>Male subordinate associates.</catDesc>
                                    <category id="boy">
                                        <catDesc>Associate male children of any class.</catDesc>
                                    </category>
                                    
                                    
                                </category>
                                
                                
                            </category>
                            
                          <category id="superior">
                              <catDesc>Associate (non-family) who has authority, mentor, model, employer.</catDesc>
                              <category id="superior_female">
                                  <catDesc>female authority figure</catDesc>
                              </category>
                              <category id="superior_male">
                                  <catDesc>male authority figure</catDesc>
                              </category>
                              
                              
                          </category>
                        
                        </category>
                        
                        
                     
                    </category>
                    

                
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    </encodingDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="social_status">
                <category id="genealogy">
                    <catDesc>Information about ancestry.</catDesc>
                    <category id="origins_upper_class">
                        <catDesc>Indications of higher status or wealth in family history.</catDesc>
                    </category>
                
                <category id="origins_lower_class">
                    <catDesc>Indications of lower status or wealth in family history.</catDesc>
                    
                    </category>
                    
                    </category>
                 <category id="quality">
                     <catDesc>Non-genealogical signs of class or status.</catDesc>
                 </category>
                
                
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2009-09-29">September 29, 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<name id="aec6v">Andrew Curley, University of Virginia Library</name>
<resp>corrector</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>Minor corrections to vendor markup.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="t1">
<body id="t1-body">
<div1 type="part" id="d3">
<pb n="28"/>
<head>SISTER DORA, <lb/>
WALSALL'S TRUEST AND BEST FRIEND.</head>
<div2 type="chapter" n="I" id="d4">
<head>CHAPTER I.</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d5">
<head>Childhood.</head>
<p corresp="setting orientation beginning_family home_childhood"><hi rend="small-caps">Some</hi> eighty odd years ago the rector of <lb/>
Hauxwell, a lonely village near Richmond, <lb/>
in the North Riding of Yorkshire, was the <lb/>
    <anchor corresp="father"/>Rev. <name>Mark James Pattison</name>, a man of much <reg orig="learn-|ing">learning</reg>, <lb/>
and descended <lb/>
from a very old <lb/>
Devonshire family. <lb/>
The rectory, a <reg orig="charm-|ing">charming</reg> <lb/>
house not far <lb/>
from the church, was <lb/>
perhaps one of the <lb/>
happiest homesteads <lb/>
in that remote little <lb/>
parish.</p>
<figure id="f1" rend="block"/>
<p>All day long, laugh <lb/>
and song and the <lb/>
patter of childish feet could be heard within its <lb/>
walls, and of the little Pattisons perhaps the <lb/>
gayest and most winsome was Dorothy. The <lb/>
children were carefully trained by their parents <lb/>
to be kind and helpful to those in need, to be <lb/>
obedient and dutiful at home, and courteous to all.</p>
<p>Now Dorothy, as a young child, being far from <lb/>
strong, was never given any regular instruction, <lb/>
but, being most observant, she <hi rend="italic">thought</hi> about all <lb/>
that she saw, and thus learned much more than <lb/>
might have been expected. These thoughtful <lb/>
<pb n="29"/>
moods were noticeable only when Dorothy was <lb/>
not feeling well, for at other times she was full <lb/>
of fun and frolic, and never so happy as when <lb/>
devising some bit of mischief.</p>
<p>One point in her character became clear when <lb/>
she was still young. If she made up her mind <lb/>
to do a certain thing, nothing turned her from her <lb/>
purpose; she made no fuss when opposed, but, in <lb/>
a quiet way, managed to attain her end.</p>
<p>Many children would have been very much <lb/>
cast down by so much illness; but Dorothy <lb/>
Pattison had the happy faculty of always looking <lb/>
on the bright side of things, so that an illness <lb/>
over was soon forgotten. When about fourteen <lb/>
years of age, she was so dangerously ill that it <lb/>
was a long time before she fully recovered.</p>
<p>During this time she suffered intense pain, but <lb/>
she bore it with so much patience and sweetness as <lb/>
to win golden opinions from her nurses. The <reg orig="self-|control">self-control</reg> <lb/>
and power of endurance thus early shown <lb/>
she retained to the end of her life, and there is no <lb/>
doubt that these characteristics helped her through <lb/>
trials which repelled those unfortunate enough to <lb/>
lack them.</p>
<p>From this time Dorothy's health improved <lb/>
wonderfully, and she was able to take her share <lb/>
of the duties that all the Pattison children were <lb/>
taught they owed to their poorer neighbours. <lb/>
Fortunately, they had the means to do a great <lb/>
deal of good, for their mother was the daughter <lb/>
of a Richmond banker, named Winn, whose <lb/>
family was noted for great liberality.</p>
<p>Dorothy and her sisters felt that to give away <lb/>
<pb n="30"/>
what needed no sacrifice on their part was not <lb/>
true giving; so they frequently wore their clothes <lb/>
till quite shabby in order to give the money thus <lb/>
saved to the poor. It is also said that they <lb/>
sometimes ate bread and cheese themselves so as <lb/>
to give their good dinners to others. It was a <lb/>
common thing to see them carrying tins of hot <lb/>
soup to the poor cottagers in the winter-time. <lb/>
Indeed, they spared neither bodily effort nor <lb/>
power of mind, in their anxiety to do good, and <lb/>
the people of the village grew to love them.</p>
<p>Once, when Dorothy was away from home, one <lb/>
of the village boys fell ill with typhoid fever. His <lb/>
one wish was to see "Miss Dora," as he called her, <lb/>
and the poor child listened anxiously every day <lb/>
for her carriage wheels. At last she came, and he <lb/>
was the first to hear her. "There's Miss Dora! <lb/>
There she is!" he cried, and, exhausted by the <lb/>
effort, fell back on his pillow.</p>
<p>She went to him at once and remained to the <lb/>
end, nursing him with loving care, and cheering <lb/>
him with her bright smile and comforting words. <lb/>
This was the first time she had done anything of <lb/>
the sort, and even then she was more influenced by <lb/>
the desire to be kind than by the child's suffering.</p>
<p>She was now growing tall and strong like her <lb/>
father, and beautiful of face like her mother. <lb/>
She delighted in games of all kinds, but <reg orig="par-|ticularly">particularly</reg> <lb/>
those best suited to boys. Nothing <lb/>
gave her so much pleasure as a good gallop <lb/>
across the moors, or a ride to hounds with her <lb/>
brothers. Whatever she did, whether work or <lb/>
play, she did with her whole heart: there were <lb/>
<pb n="31"/>
no half measures with Dorothy Pattison; if a <lb/>
thing were worth doing, she did it well.</p>
<p>Having a fine voice and a great love for music, <lb/>
she undertook to train the village choir; and, in <lb/>
later years, she comforted many a poor sufferer by <lb/>
singing as she bustled about her many duties. <lb/>
An old friend describes her as "a bright, bonnie <lb/>
maiden, singing about the house." So she grew <lb/>
up to be a cheerful, active, shrewd woman, <lb/>
resolute, steadfast of purpose, and, above all, kind, <lb/>
thoughtful, and sympathetic, with the enviable <lb/>
faculty of forgetting herself in the good of others.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="II" id="d6">
<head>CHAPTER II.</head>
<div3 type="part" id="d7">
<head>First Efforts.</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">It</hi> was not at all likely that so energetic a girl <lb/>
as Dorothy Pattison could long be satisfied <lb/>
with the placid inactivity of her quiet home. <lb/>
She seemed now to fully realise the amount of <lb/>
human suffering there is in the world, and <lb/>
longed with an intense yearning to do <reg orig="some-|thing">something</reg> <lb/>
to relieve it. It is not, therefore, surprising <lb/>
that she earnestly desired to join the band of <lb/>
devoted women who accompanied Miss Florence <lb/>
Nightingale to the Crimea.</p>
<p>Hitherto she had never shown any wish to <lb/>
nurse the sick, nor was it apparent that she had <lb/>
any special ability to do so, while it was quite <lb/>
certain that she had neither training nor <reg orig="experi-|ence">experience</reg> <lb/>
in such work. Her father pointed all this <lb/>
<pb n="32"/>	
out to her, advising her to do her duty at home <lb/>
and she would have little time to spare.</p>
<p>In this he was right, for her mother, being now <lb/>
an invalid, needed a great deal of attention; and <lb/>
so Dorothy quietly took her share of the nursing, <lb/>
and was so bright and happy about the house <lb/>
that her father called her his "sunshine." Yet <lb/>
all the while, in her steadfast way, she never <reg orig="for-|sook">forsook</reg> <lb/>
her purpose. Occasionally she visited her <lb/>
elder brother, Mark, at Lincoln College, Oxford, <lb/>
proving herself both useful and entertaining, and <lb/>
from him she learned much that went toward <lb/>
making her the noble woman whose memory we <lb/>
hold so sacred.</p>
<p>In the year 1861 her mother died, and Dorothy, <lb/>
having now no place in her home which she felt <lb/>
obliged to fill, was once more consumed with the <lb/>
desire to do her share in the world's work. She <lb/>
had felt much drawn toward a certain sisterhood <lb/>
of Good Samaritans, who, among other charitable <lb/>
works, conducted a convalescent home at Coatham, <lb/>
near Redcar in Yorkshire.</p>
<p>Finding that her father had a very strong <lb/>
objection to her joining the sisterhood, she <lb/>
refrained at that time from doing so, although <lb/>
thoroughly determined that some useful work she <lb/>
must and would find. A mistress was needed for <lb/>
the village school at Woolston, in <reg orig="Buckingham-|shire">Buckinghamshire</reg>, <lb/>
and this post Dorothy Pattison offered to <lb/>
fill. Her father did not take kindly to the idea, <lb/>
and told her that he should only continue her <lb/>
usual allowance of money.</p>
<p>This, however, did not turn her from her purpose, <lb/>
<pb n="33"/>
and so, in order to have something to spare for <lb/>
those in need, she managed to do all but the very <lb/>
heaviest of the work of her little cottage herself.</p>
<p>At Woolston she soon won the affection and <lb/>
esteem not only of the children she taught, but <lb/>
also of the inhabitants of the village: and here <lb/>
she began that self-sacrifice which marked the <lb/>
whole of her after-life. During the three years <lb/>
spent at Woolston she proved herself not only <lb/>
an earnest, lovable schoolmistress, but a friend <lb/>
to anyone in need of such.</p>
<p>In fact she worked so hard, teaching by day and <lb/>
nursing the sick by night, that her health gave <lb/>
way. She became low-spirited and filled with the <lb/>
thought that she was not doing enough for those <lb/>
around her. This weakness and depression ended <lb/>
in a sharp attack of pleurisy, and, as soon as she <lb/>
was well enough to travel, she went to Redcar to <lb/>
recover her strength. Her sympathy with the <lb/>
work of the sisterhood revived, and Dorothy now <lb/>
resolved to join the Good Samaritans.</p>
<p>Her family knew well that the necessary <reg orig="restric-|tions">restrictions</reg> <lb/>
of such a body would not suit Dorothy's <lb/>
temperament, but all their persuasions availed <lb/>
nothing; she had made up her mind to join, <lb/>
and join she would and did, only to prove in <lb/>
time that her friends knew her better than she <lb/>
knew herself. Yet so attentively and intelligently <lb/>
did she perform all the duties required of her, that <lb/>
none even guessed she had made a mistake.</p>
<p>Her sweet graciousness of manner, sunny smile, <lb/>
and earnest devotion to duty soon won for "Sister <lb/>
Dora," as she was now called, the love of all with <lb/>
<pb n="34"/>
whom she came in contact. Her first knowledge <lb/>
of hospital work was gained at North Ormesby, <lb/>
Yorkshire; but in 1865 she was sent to Walsall, <lb/>
in South Staffordshire, where she shortly <reg orig="after-|wards">afterwards</reg> <lb/>
found her life's work.</p>
<p>The cottage hospital in this town had been <lb/>
established about a year, and during that time <lb/>
had been conducted by the sisterhood of Good <lb/>
Samaritans in the face of the most obstinate <lb/>
opposition of the people whom it was meant to <lb/>
benefit. They had an intense dislike of Roman <lb/>
Catholicism, to which faith they believed the sisters <lb/>
belonged, and showed it in a very unmistakable <lb/>
way. Sister Dora was, perhaps, the last to suffer <lb/>
from their active opposition.</p>
<p>While walking along a street one day a lad threw <lb/>
a stone at her, making a nasty cut on her forehead. <lb/>
Now Sister Dora, having once seen a face, never <lb/>
forgot it; and so it happened that when one day, <lb/>
some time later, this same lad was taken into the <lb/>
hospital seriously hurt, she knew him at once. <lb/>
All the skill at her command, and the care and <lb/>
loving attention of which she was capable, she <lb/>
lavished upon him; and so utterly ashamed of <lb/>
his brutality toward her did the lad feel, that he <lb/>
was not happy till he had confessed his fault and <lb/>
obtained her forgiveness</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="III" id="d8">
<pb n="35"/>
<head>CHAPTER III.</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d9">
<head>The Friend of the People.</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">Sister dora</hi> now returned to Coatham, and <lb/>
was shortly afterwards chosen by an eminent <lb/>
physician to take charge of a most difficult <lb/>
case. The patient was an eccentric old lady, who, <lb/>
becoming very much attached to her nurse, wished <lb/>
to make her some very valuable presents. These <lb/>
were at first graciously but firmly refused, but <lb/>
finding that this vexed her patient greatly, Sister <lb/>
Dora afterwards took them from her and then <lb/>
secretly restored them to the family. Upon the <lb/>
death of this old lady Sister Dora returned to <lb/>
Walsall, where, with few intervals, she continued <lb/>
to work for thirteen years.</p>
<p>She suited the doctors so well that they begged <lb/>
the sisters to be allowed to keep her altogether; but <lb/>
this they were not disposed to do. She was ordered <lb/>
to go at once to Devonshire, to nurse a private <lb/>
patient; but, before starting, she received news <lb/>
that her father was dangerously ill, and wished <lb/>
to see her very much. On applying for leave to <lb/>
go home, the sisters replied that her orders were <lb/>
to proceed immediately to Devonshire, which she <lb/>
did with a very sore heart.</p>
<p>On arriving, news reached her that her father <lb/>
was dead, and that it was her duty to attend the <lb/>
funeral. Permission to do so came from Coatham; <lb/>
but Sister Dora felt that as she had not been <lb/>
allowed to see her father while still alive, she had <lb/>
<pb n="36"/>
no desire to avail herself of such permission. She <lb/>
therefore diligently fulfilled the duties required of <lb/>
her until she was no longer needed, when she once <lb/>
more returned to Walsall.</p>
<p>From this time she ceased to take any deep <lb/>
interest in the sisterhood of Good Samaritans, <lb/>
though she remained one of them for some years <lb/>
longer. She now set herself to study diligently <lb/>
all the details of her profession, and so great was <lb/>
her earnestness and intelligence that she attracted <lb/>
the attention of an old doctor, who taught her <lb/>
all he knew of surgery.</p>
<p>She eventually became not only a skilful surgeon <lb/>
but a successful one, for she inspired her patients <lb/>
with such unbounded confidence in her power to <lb/>
heal them, that they willingly agreed to all she <lb/>
suggested.</p>
<p>The employment of the people of this district <lb/>
being very productive of accidents to the eye, she <lb/>
determined to take a course of lectures at the <lb/>
Ophthalmic Hospital, Birmingham, so as to be <lb/>
able to deal with such cases. There was no <lb/>
resident surgeon in the Walsall hospital, and so it <lb/>
fell to Sister Dora to treat all casualties brought <lb/>
in; and this was one reason why she was so <lb/>
anxious to learn all that could possibly help in <lb/>
the immediate alleviation of pain. So thorough <lb/>
a knowledge of both theoretical and practical <lb/>
surgery did she at last obtain that she was <reg orig="con-|sidered">considered</reg> <lb/>
to be much cleverer than many ordinary <lb/>
doctors.</p>
<p>And all this time she was fighting inward <lb/>
battles with herself&mdash;battles in which self-pleasing <lb/>
<pb n="37"/>
and self-abnegation were strongly opposed. Should <lb/>
she, forgetting all that a home of her own and <lb/>
the society of cultivated people would be to her, <lb/>
continue the work she had begun so well, and <lb/>
devote the whole of her life to the needs of the <lb/>
sick, the poor, and the friendless?</p>
<p>Would she have sufficient strength of mind to <lb/>
withstand future temptation of similar kind, or <lb/>
should she, by joining a stricter sisterhood, remove <lb/>
herself beyond the power of such temptation?</p>
<p>In her difficulty she sought the advice of an <lb/>
old friend, who pointed out to her how peculiarly <lb/>
suited she was to the work she had undertaken, <lb/>
and that he thought she would certainly find her <lb/>
chief happiness in promoting the welfare of those <lb/>
suffering ones to whom her heart had really been <lb/>
given, rather than in yielding to a passing fancy <lb/>
which would, all too soon, prove unsatisfying to a <lb/>
nature such as hers.</p>
<p>So, in her quiet, purposeful manner, she <reg orig="con-|tinued">continued</reg> <lb/>
her hospital work until, in 1866, she had a <lb/>
very serious illness. Then the people realised all <lb/>
that she had become to them; they felt that she <lb/>
was <hi rend="italic">their</hi> friend, and they could not spare her. <lb/>
Who but Sister Dora would come to them at any <lb/>
hour of the night to set a broken limb, to bandage <lb/>
a gaping wound, to soothe a riotous drunkard, or <lb/>
comfort the last moments of the dying?</p>
<p>Many anxious inquiries were made at the door <lb/>
of the hospital, and prayers were offered on her <lb/>
behalf at the church of St. James, Wednesbury.</p>
<p>Now Sister Dora had an almost superstitious <lb/>
belief in the power of prayer, and so she liked to <lb/>
<pb n="38"/>
think that her recovery was due to these petitions <lb/>
of the people, and she loved them even more than <lb/>
before.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="IV" id="d10">
<head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d11">
<head>A Few of the Actions that Won their Hearts.</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">The</hi> hospital committee now decided to erect <lb/>
a new building, as the old one was not only <lb/>
too small for the needs of the people but <lb/>
was very badly placed for purposes of ventilation. <lb/>
Sister Dora gave a good contribution towards the <lb/>
expenses, and the rest of the money was soon <lb/>
obtained. A site was chosen on the hill on <lb/>
which the parish church stands; the work went <lb/>
steadily forward, and, in 1868, the new hospital <lb/>
was ready.</p>
<p>It was divided into three wards, and contained <lb/>
twenty-eight beds&mdash;with convenience for more, if <lb/>
needed&mdash;good accommodation for out-door patients, <lb/>
and every appliance known at that time. It was <lb/>
so arranged that one active person could manage <lb/>
the whole of the nursing, and this Sister Dora did.</p>
<p>She washed the patients, made their beds, dressed <lb/>
their wounds, fed them, sewed for them, read to <lb/>
them, played games with them in her rare intervals <lb/>
of leisure, and never omitted prayers even on the <lb/>
busiest mornings, standing in such a position that <lb/>
the patients in all the wards could hear her. She <lb/>
taught them to go to God in all their trials, and <lb/>
impressed on their minds that if they really had <lb/>
faith. He would grant their requests.</p>
<pb n="39"/>
<p>She was never wearied by their wants, and waited <lb/>
upon them as willingly by night as by day. Her <lb/>
sunny smile, her winsome manner, her ever-present <lb/>
cheeriness and ready sympathy helped greatly <lb/>
toward the recovery of many of the poor sufferers <lb/>
under her care. One man said of her, "Make <lb/>
you laugh? She'd make you laugh if you were <lb/>
dying!"</p>
<p>Many of the poor men sought to <unclear id="u1">relieve</unclear> their <lb/>
feelings, when in great pain, by using bad <lb/>
language, but this Sister Dora would by no means <lb/>
allow. "Stop that!" she would say; "if you <lb/>
really must say something, say <hi rend="italic">poker and tongs!"</hi> <lb/>
Then looking round with a bright face, she would <lb/>
add, "Now remember, nothing but <hi rend="italic">poker and <lb/>
tongs!"</hi> and away she would go, feeling confident <lb/>
that she would be obeyed.</p>
<p>Just at this time small-pox broke out in the town <lb/>
and spread rapidly, so that Sister Dora had plenty <lb/>
to do outside the hospital. She never refused to <lb/>
attend a case, and the more loathsome it was the <lb/>
more readily did she render help. One night she <lb/>
was sent for to a man who was dying of the <reg orig="black-|pox">black-pox</reg>. <lb/>
His wife and friends had all deserted him, <lb/>
and he was alone in a house situated in one of <lb/>
the worst slums of the town.</p>
<p>On reaching the wretched dwelling she found <lb/>
that there was but one small piece of candle left; <lb/>
so she gave a woman some money to buy some <lb/>
more for her. The woman failed to bring the <lb/>
candles, and so the good sister sat the whole of <lb/>
the night alone and in darkness with the poor <lb/>
diseased and dying man.</p>
<pb n="40"/>
<p>Once during the long hours he said to her, <lb/>
"Kiss me before I die, sister!" and, putting her <lb/>
arms around the poor fellow, heedless of disease, <lb/>
she granted his last request. Shortly afterwards <lb/>
he passed peacefully away, but still she sat on, <lb/>
until, when the dawn broke, she called in some <lb/>
neighbours and returned to the hospital.</p>
<p>About this time an old servant of the Pattison <lb/>
family went to help Sister Dora in her work, and <lb/>
soon became very useful both in managing the <lb/>
domestic arrangements and in nursing.</p>
<p>Some of the patients taken into the institution <lb/>
were terribly crushed by explosions in mines and <lb/>
accidents with machinery&mdash;so much so that it was <lb/>
often found necessary to take off a limb as a last <lb/>
means of saving life. Now these poor men did not <lb/>
at all like the idea of amputation, and a great deal <lb/>
of persuasion was needed to gain their consent to <lb/>
such an operation. This usually fell to Sister <lb/>
Dora, for few could resist her charm of manner <lb/>
and quiet though sensible reasoning.</p>
<p>On one occasion, however, she strongly objected <lb/>
to the removal of the arm of a fine young fellow <lb/>
who had met with a terrible accident. His right <lb/>
arm was twisted and torn dreadfully, but Sister <lb/>
Dora's keen eye saw a chance of saving it, and <lb/>
she said so. The doctor found it impossible to <lb/>
agree with her, and, after a time, gave up the case <lb/>
entirely.</p>
<p>The whole responsibility was now undertaken by <lb/>
Sister Dora, and it is very certain that she spent <lb/>
some very anxious days until the result proved that <lb/>
her idea had been a true one. She saved the arm, <lb/>
<pb n="41"/>
and with most pardonable pride fetched the doctor <lb/>
to see it, at the end of a fortnight. His <reg orig="astonish-|ment">astonishment</reg> <lb/>
was unbounded, and it is but fair to him <lb/>
to say that he was as pleased as if the credit had <lb/>
been his own.</p>
<p>The young fellow ever afterward called that arm <lb/>
"Sister's arm," and so attached was he to the <lb/>
clever woman who had done so much for him, that <lb/>
some time later, when she was very ill, he walked <lb/>
eleven miles into Walsall every Sunday to inquire <lb/>
for her. Before leaving he always said to the <lb/>
servant, "Tell sister that was <hi rend="italic">her</hi> arm that rang <lb/>
the bell!"</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="V" id="d12">
<head>CHAPTER V.</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d13">
<head>Her Influence over the People.</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">Some</hi> of the greatest battles Sister Dora fought <lb/>
were against bad language and drunkenness. <lb/>
Big brawny men hung their heads at her <lb/>
rebuke; coarse jest and foul words died on the <lb/>
lips at her approach; even the poor misguided <lb/>
drunkard tried to straighten himself and walk as <lb/>
a man if she were near.</p>
<p>Alone, at the dead of night, in the lowest <lb/>
slums of the town she walked without fear&mdash;a <lb/>
woman such as those poor degraded people had <lb/>
never before dreamed of. They believed in her <lb/>
and they loved her; and they were right in doing <lb/>
so, for she gave them all of her best, and none <lb/>
could do more.</p>
<p>Many men and women left the hospital resolved <lb/>
<pb n="42"/>
upon leading better lives for her sake, and to <lb/>
many such she gave ample means of beginning <lb/>
over again in a new world, far removed from <lb/>
old associations and temptations.</p>
<p>The outbreak of war between France and <lb/>
Germany again made her feel that among the <lb/>
wounded and the dying on the stricken field of <lb/>
battle she could find even more to do for God than <lb/>
in Walsall, but, happily for that town, the feeling <lb/>
passed; she found it impossible to leave the people <lb/>
to whom she had grown so dear, and whom she <lb/>
loved with all the depth of her large heart.</p>
<p>Among the convalescents in the hospital she had <lb/>
ever one who hung on her slightest wish, and I <lb/>
feel sure you will be interested to hear about him. <lb/>
He was a poor little fellow of ten, named Sam. He <lb/>
was more than ordinarily sharp and observant, so <lb/>
that, after a time, he was able to prepare for Sister <lb/>
Dora all that she would need in ordinary cases.</p>
<p>One morning he was suffering such intense pain <lb/>
that he felt unable to leave his bed. The poor <lb/>
child hid his head beneath the clothes, that Sister <lb/>
Dora should not be worried by the tears he could <lb/>
not restrain. She knew all about it, however, and, <lb/>
in a little while, she said aloud to another patient, <lb/>
"Tell Sam I <hi rend="italic">do</hi> miss him!" Instantly the trouble <lb/>
left the dear boy's face, and, having dressed <reg orig="him-|self">himself</reg>, <lb/>
he went to help the sister as brightly as if <lb/>
there were no such thing as pain in all the world.</p>
<p>Sometimes, looking very gravely at him, she <lb/>
would say, in reference to a wound she was <lb/>
treating, "Now, doctor, what would you do in this <lb/>
case?" and, quite as gravely, Sam would reply, <lb/>
<pb/>
<pb/>
<figure id="f2" rend="page"/>
<pb n="43"/>
"Zinc ointment!" or any other remedy he knew <lb/>
from experience she would be likely to use.</p>
<p>Sister Dora's winsome way with children <lb/>
especially was delightful to see. Poor little mites <lb/>
badly scalded, and brought to her for help, held out <lb/>
their tiny arms and nestled against her bosom as <lb/>
soon as they saw her, and many a sorrowing <lb/>
mother returned to her wretched home with the <lb/>
full assurance that all that human skill and <lb/>
womanly love could do for her suffering child <lb/>
would be done by that great-hearted, capable <lb/>
woman, Sister Dora.</p>
<p>The miserable, neglected little children of the <lb/>
courts and alleys ran smiling to her, knowing well <lb/>
that <hi rend="italic">Sister</hi> would have a kiss for them. She was, <lb/>
indeed, a <hi rend="italic">sister</hi> to them, and much more, for one <lb/>
of her humble friends said of her, after her death, <lb/>
that she was as like the Lord Jesus Christ as any <lb/>
human creature could be.</p>
<p>One day a dear little girl was brought into the <lb/>
hospital suffering from such dreadful burns that <lb/>
she could not possibly recover. So Sister Dora <lb/>
sat down by the child's bed and told her pretty <lb/>
stories of Heaven and Jesus and the happy angels, <lb/>
until, looking sweetly into the good sister's face, <lb/>
the poor little child said, "When you come to <lb/>
heaven, sister, I will meet you at the gate with <lb/>
a bunch of flowers."</p>
<p>Many of the local railway-men owed both life <lb/>
and limb to her skill, and so, as a token of <lb/>
esteem they bought and presented to her a small <lb/>
carriage and pony. She was greatly touched by <lb/>
their thoughtfulness; and she found the carriage <lb/>
<pb n="44"/>
very useful, not only in taking convalescent <lb/>
patients for drives into the country, but also in <lb/>
saving time in her many errands of mercy <reg orig="out-|side">outside</reg> <lb/>
the hospital.</p>
<p>In the autumn of the year 1874 her connection <lb/>
with the sisters of the <hi rend="italic">Good Samaritans</hi> ceased. <lb/>
From this time Sister Dora's one great wish <lb/>
was to establish a convalescent home for her <lb/>
patients on the north coast of Wales, as she firmly <lb/>
believed in the healing powers of sea air and <lb/>
bathing, when possible. Such a home now <lb/>
actually exists at Abergele, though unhappily <lb/>
Sister Dora did not live to see it. She was very <lb/>
fond of the water herself, and it is said that during <lb/>
one of her visits to Redcar she saved a woman <lb/>
from drowning by swimming out to her and <lb/>
holding her head above water till help came.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="VI" id="d14">
<head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d15">
<head>Her Management of the Epidemic Hospital.</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">After</hi> the last outbreak of small-pox the <lb/>
hospital committee erected an isolation <lb/>
building outside the town, but, when in <lb/>
1875 the disease again appeared, the people <lb/>
absolutely refused to go there. At length Sister <lb/>
Dora wrote to the mayor, offering to take charge <lb/>
of the isolated hospital, and you may be quite <lb/>
sure that her offer was joyfully accepted.</p>
<p>As soon as the people heard that <hi rend="italic">sister</hi> would <lb/>
nurse them, they went readily enough to the <lb/>
<pb n="45"/>
hospital, and so firm a hold had the disease now <lb/>
obtained that all the beds were soon full. Then it <lb/>
was that Dorothy Pattison thanked God with all <lb/>
her heart for the strength and power of endurance <lb/>
He had given her&mdash;for both were tried to the very <lb/>
utmost.</p>
<p>With none but two old women from the <reg orig="work-|house">work-house</reg> <lb/>
to help with the washing, and an old man to <lb/>
act as porter, she did the whole of the work of <lb/>
nursing, washing, cooking for and feeding <reg orig="twenty-|eight">twenty-eight</reg> <lb/>
patients in every stage of the disease. In many <lb/>
cases she was obliged even to make clothes for them; <lb/>
and the babies were a source of constant labour.</p>
<p>Yet her native cheerfulness never forsook her, <lb/>
for in one letter she says, "You would laugh to <lb/>
see me washing my babies. Poor things! they <lb/>
are getting quite fond of me; but they do make <lb/>
some washing!" Yet, in spite of her many <lb/>
duties, she found "time and opportunity to <lb/>
spread the glad tidings to many an ignorant <lb/>
soul;" and she thanked God for her daily life <lb/>
in that abode of disease and death.</p>
<p>When the last patient left the epidemic hospital, <lb/>
some six months later, she returned to the scene of <lb/>
her former labours, and shortly afterwards one of <lb/>
the most fearful accidents the town has ever known <lb/>
occurred in Walsall. An explosion took place at <lb/>
some ironworks near by, and eleven men were <lb/>
literally covered with molten metal.</p>
<p>Hoping to ease their agony they jumped into <lb/>
a canal close at hand, and were rescued with the <lb/>
greatest difficulty. A ward was soon cleared at <lb/>
the hospital for their reception, and then began <lb/>
<pb n="46"/>
such a labour of mercy that many a strong man and <lb/>
woman was forced to turn from it, sick and faint.</p>
<p>So ghastly were the wounds of the poor fellows <lb/>
that even Sister Dora could not manage without <lb/>
taking a little brandy as a stimulant. For ten <lb/>
days and nights did this brave woman battle with <lb/>
death, and, in the end, was successful in saving <lb/>
the lives of two of the unfortunate sufferers. One <lb/>
of these two in speaking of her says: "She was <lb/>
with us almost night and day. It did you good <lb/>
only to look at her. What we felt for her I <lb/>
couldn't tell you, my tongue won't say it."</p>
<p>The ward in which these poor men had lain was <lb/>
so full of poisonous germs that no wounds would <lb/>
thereafter heal in it. The committee, therefore, <lb/>
determined to build a new and larger hospital. <lb/>
A temporary building was taken, sufficiently large <lb/>
to hold twelve beds, with very scanty <reg orig="accommoda-|tion">accommodation</reg> <lb/>
for the nursing staff, and none for out-patients, <lb/>
who were therefore obliged to receive attention at <lb/>
their old quarters in the condemned hospital.</p>
<p>In 1876 Sister Dora did a great deal of good <lb/>
work among the poor outcast women of the town. <lb/>
A mission was being held, and she added largely <lb/>
to its success by personally conducting the <lb/>
missionaries into the worst haunts of sin and <lb/>
misery. They could never have reached these <lb/>
people alone, for it would have been more than <lb/>
their lives were worth to have ventured into such <lb/>
districts without the protecting care of the woman <lb/>
whom even the vilest men revered.</p>
<p>In the winter of 1877 she discovered that she was <lb/>
suffering from a disease which must end fatally. <lb/>
<pb n="47"/>
Binding her medical adviser to secrecy, she <reg orig="con-|tinued">continued</reg> <lb/>
her labours of love, to all appearance just <lb/>
as strong and healthy as ever. The following <lb/>
Christmas she determined to give her people such <lb/>
a happy time that they would never forget it, for <lb/>
she felt sure that it was her last chance of seeing <lb/>
them thoroughly enjoying themselves.</p>
<p>She threw herself heartily into their games; and <lb/>
no one to look at her could have guessed that the <lb/>
tall, handsome woman would, almost inevitably, <lb/>
pass from the scene of her earthly efforts, to take <lb/>
her share of joy in the kingdom above ere another <lb/>
Christmas Day had dawned.</p>
<p>Knowing how short her time was, she worked <lb/>
with a restless activity that astounded even the <lb/>
hospital committee, accustomed as they were to <lb/>
her untiring energy. She now found her little <lb/>
carriage most useful, for she was frequently called <lb/>
to places quite ten miles from the town.</p>
<p>One night as the old porter was driving her along <lb/>
a quiet country road, a man sprang out of the hedge, <lb/>
and, coming up behind, struck at Sister Dora with <lb/>
a heavy stick. She swerved her head aside just in <lb/>
time to save herself, while the ruffian, hearing the <lb/>
sound of horse-hoofs approaching, made off quickly.</p>
<p>This was but one of the adventures with which <lb/>
she met. But the old porter always said that the <lb/>
man must have been a stranger, for he knew that <lb/>
no Walsall man would touch Sister Dora to do her <lb/>
any harm; and I think he was right. Nothing <lb/>
daunted her, however, and she continued her <reg orig="mid-|night">midnight</reg> <lb/>
journeys as usual, for she had really no time <lb/>
during the day to spare outside the town.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="VII" id="d16">
<pb n="48"/>
<head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d17">
<head>Sister Dora's Last Efforts.</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">The</hi> disease had now become so painful that <lb/>
Sister Dora was obliged to consult a <reg orig="Birming-|ham">Birmingham</reg> <lb/>
doctor, in whose opinion she had implicit <lb/>
confidence. From him she learned that the dread <lb/>
cancer had now reached that stage which needed <lb/>
surgical treatment. True to her determination to <lb/>
let none know of her trouble till it was impossible <lb/>
longer to conceal it, she bravely dressed the wound <lb/>
herself and resumed her duties.</p>
<p>Just at this time she was asked by a doctor to <lb/>
assist at an operation on the throat of a child <lb/>
suffering from diphtheria. An incision was made <lb/>
and a silver tube inserted to enable the child to <lb/>
breathe more freely. The little throat was filled <lb/>
with poisonous mucus, and Sister Dora, kneeling <lb/>
beside the child, actually sucked the deadly matter <lb/>
through the incision! The patient recovered from <lb/>
that illness, but at the cost of three weeks' acute <lb/>
suffering to the brave sister.</p>
<p>In June, 1878, upon returning from a short <lb/>
holiday, Sister Dora found it necessary to close <lb/>
the temporary hospital, owing to an outbreak of <lb/>
typhoid fever. The new building not being <lb/>
finished, she decided to have a good long rest <lb/>
among her friends; but, before starting, she took <lb/>
all her old patients and the hospital staff for an <lb/>
outing to Lichfield. She had taken them on many <lb/>
such trips before, but all agreed that they had <lb/>
<pb n="49"/>
never seen her so utterly happy and gay as she <lb/>
was on that particular occasion.</p>
<p>Her nieces, too, with whom she afterwards went <lb/>
to stay, remarked the same thing. She seemed <lb/>
even fuller of life than usual, teaching them to <lb/>
swim, and playing many a trick upon them while <lb/>
in the water, so that they had not the faintest idea <lb/>
that she was suffering from a disease that would <lb/>
soon prove fatal.</p>
<p>She next went to Paris, where she visited the <lb/>
Exhibition; afterwards returning to London, with <lb/>
the intention of attending a course of lectures on <lb/>
the treatment of wounds, by Professor Lister. <lb/>
Really she should have been quietly resting at <lb/>
home; for, during her stay in London, her pain <lb/>
increased so rapidly and her cough became so <lb/>
very troublesome, that it was patent to all she was <lb/>
suffering from some malignant form of disease.</p>
<p>Seeing that there was danger of her secret being <lb/>
discovered, she suddenly left London for <reg orig="Birming-|ham">Birmingham</reg>. <lb/>
Now, in her state at that time, such a journey <lb/>
was almost certain death; but, in spite of the grave <lb/>
fears of the doctor, she rallied sufficiently to be <lb/>
taken to Walsall&mdash;to die, as she herself wished, <lb/>
among her own people.</p>
<p>The hospital committee prepared a house for her <lb/>
reception, and an old servant was engaged to wait <lb/>
upon and nurse her; but, although the sad news of <lb/>
her illness spread rapidly in the town, no breath of <lb/>
the real trouble was allowed to get abroad. The <lb/>
people absolutely refused to believe that Sister <lb/>
Dora would never more minister to their needs; <lb/>
they seemed to think that she was a being superior <lb/>
<pb n="50"/>
to such things as sickness and death; but, when <lb/>
they fully realised the mournful truth, the whole <lb/>
town seemed utterly cast down.</p>
<p>She was now compelled to accept the help of <lb/>
Mrs. H., the old family servant who had been of <lb/>
so much use to her in the hospital, but it was with <lb/>
the greatest reluctance that Sister Dora confided the <lb/>
nature of her trouble even to her. She was gratified <lb/>
by the visits of her sisters, but would not hear of <lb/>
their remaining to nurse her, and it was with aching <lb/>
hearts that they returned to their homes.</p>
<p>Perhaps we may feel inclined to blame her for <lb/>
being so reticent with her own family, but, should <lb/>
it be so, let us remember that her whole life had <lb/>
been one of self-restraint and self-reliance. With <lb/>
an almost painful reluctance to admit that <reg orig="suffer-|ing">suffering</reg> <lb/>
could subdue even her proud spirit, she had <lb/>
striven to conceal her ailments till absolutely forced <lb/>
to give in; yet, all the while, she had secretly <lb/>
dreaded that she would most certainly fall a prey <lb/>
to one of the deadly diseases she had so frequently <lb/>
and successfully combated in others.</p>
<p>During the comparatively short time she was <lb/>
confined to her bed, her old cheeriness never <lb/>
deserted her; her sublime faith in God helped <lb/>
her even then to look on the bright side, for she <lb/>
says, in writing to a friend, "My heart is full of <lb/>
thankfulness for the Good Shepherd's care and <lb/>
tender love towards me. I have not a care; it is <lb/>
all sunshine. Oh, my dear, this peace does indeed <lb/>
pass all understanding. I have so longed to go <lb/>
home. I am so happy."</p>
<p>Although it was not possible for her to see the <lb/>
<pb n="51"/>
opening of the new hospital, she had the happiness <lb/>
of knowing it was finished and declared open, in <lb/>
her name, on 14th November 1878. It was a <lb/>
great day to her; she received many visitors, and <lb/>
was saved all anxiety as to the competent <reg orig="manage-|ment">management</reg> <lb/>
of the institution by the temporary <reg orig="appoint-|ment">appointment</reg> <lb/>
of an old pupil in whom she had every <lb/>
confidence.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="VII" id="d18">
<head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d19">
<head>Sister Dora Wins her Crown of Life.</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">It</hi> had been Sister Dora's custom to give to each <lb/>
cabman in the town some small gift every <lb/>
Christmas; but, fearing she would not be with <lb/>
them much longer, she gave them their presents of <lb/>
warm gloves, scarves, etc., in November, shortly <lb/>
after the opening of the new hospital.</p>
<p>That she should, in the midst of all her pain, <lb/>
so think of them, touched the men's hearts most <lb/>
deeply; and I have no doubt that many of these <lb/>
gifts are even now treasured as souvenirs of the <lb/>
giver, though the actual recipients needed nothing <lb/>
beyond the remembrance of years of steadfast <lb/>
devotion to them and their fellow townspeople <lb/>
to keep her memory ever green in their hearts.</p>
<p>On 24th December, 1878, she passed peacefully <lb/>
away, just in time to sing her Christmas song <lb/>
in heaven, as she so often wished. The muffled <lb/>
pealing of the church bells told the anxious people <lb/>
that the agonies of their loved one were over, and <lb/>
on the following Saturday she was laid to rest in <lb/>
<pb n="52"/>
the cemetery just beyond the town. The sad <lb/>
procession comprised members of the public <lb/>
bodies in the town, representatives of all <reg orig="pro-|fessions">professions</reg> <lb/>
and trades, bishops, clergy, and ministers <lb/>
of all denominations, in addition to hundreds and <lb/>
hundreds of people who had benefited by her skill <lb/>
and loving kindness.</p>
<p>For nearly two hours a dense crowd of all sorts <lb/>
and conditions of men, women, and children <lb/>
waited in the snow and the drizzling rain to <lb/>
see the last of her who had never failed them <lb/>
in their time of need. Tears streamed unchecked <lb/>
down the faces of rough men as the mournful <lb/>
cort&egrave;ge passed, and they gazed with uncovered <lb/>
heads upon that which contained all that was <lb/>
noble and good in womanhood to them.</p>
<p>It was in vain the police tried to check the people <lb/>
from crowding into the place of burial. Sister <lb/>
Dora was more dear to the little unwashed street <lb/>
children and the poor neglected slatternly women <lb/>
than any one else they had ever known, and they <lb/>
were there to do their last act of reverence to her <lb/>
who had shown them they had at least one friend <lb/>
in the world, and who had abundantly proved to <lb/>
them that they also had the greatest of all friends <lb/>
in heaven, the Lord Christ Jesus.</p>
<p>Though dead she yet speaks to many who knew <lb/>
and loved her; but, that her memory may live in <lb/>
the generations to come, the people have erected a <lb/>
life-sized statue of her in a prominent part of the <lb/>
town. In the hearts of the people of Walsall she <lb/>
is now, as she was nearly a quarter of a century <lb/>
ago, "<hi rend="italic">Our</hi> Sister Dora."</p>
<pb n="53"/>
<p>In the words of a minister of the town, who <lb/>
knew her well, they might also say: "Not only do <lb/>
we treasure her memory as that of a great and <lb/>
useful worker in the cause of suffering humanity, <lb/>
but for the higher reason, that we have had in her <lb/>
a style of character more sublime than any we have <lb/>
seen before, or, in these days, perhaps, hardly <lb/>
thought possible. Surely the most desirable <lb/>
image to us is that of the most perfect human <lb/>
soul, and, quite as surely, that image has dwelt <lb/>
and worked amongst us in Walsall."</p>
<p>The tomb of this noble woman is frequently <lb/>
visited by people desirous of paying a tribute of <lb/>
respect to the departed, and all are struck by its <lb/>
utter unobtrusiveness. So simple is the cross that <lb/>
marks the resting-place of the much-loving and <lb/>
much-loved sister, that many pass it by without <lb/>
even a glance.</p>
<p>The stranger, knowing her history, seeks some <lb/>
ponderous monument; but to such I would say, <lb/>
that, while her life was for many years lived <lb/>
before the public gaze, she was by nature modest <lb/>
and unassuming&mdash;never obtruding herself or her <lb/>
opinions unless assured that by so doing some <lb/>
fellow-being would be benefited.</p>
<p>No mention even of her life's work is made: the <lb/>
simple inscription being:&mdash;</p>
<p rend="center">IN MEMORY <lb/>
OF <lb/>
SISTER DORA, <lb/>
WHO ENTERED INTO REST <lb/>
ON CHRISTMAS EVE, 1878.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
