<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="UVA" rend="none"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="none"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOdia SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-dia.ent"> %ISOdia;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-tech.ent"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="UVA" rend="none">
<teiHeader type="migrated">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Creighton_Some Famous Women</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl/></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2009-09-29">September 29, 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<name id="aec6v">Andrew Curley, University of Virginia Library</name>
<resp>corrector</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>Minor corrections to vendor markup.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="t1">
<body id="t1-body">
<div1 type="chapter" n="XI" id="d3">
<pb n="156"/>
<head>XI</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d4">
<head>SISTER DORA</head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">Dorothy Pattison</hi>, who was afterwards known as Sister <lb/>
Dora, was born in 1832 in a little village called <reg orig="Haux-|well">Hauxwell</reg>, <lb/>
near Richmond, in Yorkshire, of which her father <lb/>
was the rector. She was the youngest but one of a <lb/>
family of twelve children, of whom ten were daughters. <lb/>
They grew up in all the enjoyment of country life. <lb/>
Dorothy was delicate as a child and not allowed to do <lb/>
regular lessons, but she describes herself as having all <lb/>
the same been a great romp, as wild and merry as a <lb/>
boy, and good at all outdoor sports&mdash;riding, rowing, <lb/>
shooting, swimming, and skating. But even as a tiny <lb/>
child she loved to wash and nurse her dolls, and longed <lb/>
to be able to do the same for real people. When she <lb/>
talked over the future with her nearest sister she used <lb/>
to say, "I'll be a nurse or a lady doctor and do <reg orig="every-|thing">everything</reg> <lb/>
for my patients." When she was twelve, one of <lb/>
her sisters fell ill, and Dorothy begged, at first in vain, <lb/>
to be allowed to sit up with her and nurse her, but at <lb/>
last she managed to slip into the room unnoticed, and <lb/>
once she was there, she was allowed to stay and helped <lb/>
to nurse her sister till she was well. A couple of years <lb/>
afterwards a fever broke out in the village, and an old <lb/>
woman whom Dorothy knew very well took it. She <lb/>
called at the house to ask how she was and found the <lb/>
old woman left quite alone. In a moment, she made <lb/>
<pb n="157"/>
up her mind, and without thinking of what her parents <lb/>
might say, she hung up her coat and jacket behind the <lb/>
door and told the old woman she had come to stay <lb/>
with her. In the evening she sent a message home to <lb/>
<figure id="f1" rend="page">
<head><hi rend="small-caps">Sister Dora.</hi></head>
<p>Photo: Mrs. Williams, Wolverhampton.</p>
</figure>
say that she was going to stay all night, and word came <lb/>
back that, as she had chosen to stay without permission, <lb/>
she must now remain with the old woman. She washed <lb/>
her and nursed her and read the Bible to her, but she <lb/>
grew worse and worse, and the next night she died. A <lb/>
<pb n="158"/>
kind neighbour came in and helped to lay her out, but <lb/>
Dorothy, tired out and frightened, was left to spend the <lb/>
night alone in the cottage. Next morning she sent a <lb/>
message to the Rectory to say that the poor woman <lb/>
had died, might she come home. But the answer came <lb/>
back, "Stay where you are till you are sent for." She <lb/>
was terrified lest her parents had cast her off and <lb/>
she should never be allowed to go home. But soon <lb/>
a carriage arrived with her old nurse to carry her off <lb/>
to spend a month at the seaside, so that she might be <lb/>
free from all infection before going home. When at <lb/>
last she returned home she was welcomed as a little <lb/>
heroine, and got rather puffed up by the praise she <lb/>
received.</p>
<p>As she got stronger and able to study more, she was <lb/>
inclined to rebel at the time spent over lessons, and <lb/>
said she did not see why, as she was going to be a nurse, <lb/>
she should learn languages and music. But she was <lb/>
told that a nice Christian nurse should learn everything <lb/>
she had time for; she might some day have French or <lb/>
German patients, and music would be a pleasure to <lb/>
everybody; it would not do to be one-sided, for she <lb/>
ought to be able to care for the minds and souls of her <lb/>
patients as well as for their bodies. So she was <reg orig="per-|suaded">persuaded</reg> <lb/>
to study gladly, and would often wonder how <lb/>
the thing she was learning would come in afterwards. <lb/>
Later she found that there was not a single thing she <lb/>
had learnt which had not in some way been hallowed <lb/>
in the service of God. She used to say to others, <lb/>
"Never feel that it is waste of time to get knowledge <lb/>
of any kind; you can never tell how handy it may <lb/>
come in."</p>
<p>Dora grew up to be a very handsome woman. By the <lb/>
time she was twenty, all her delicacy had disappeared <lb/>
<pb n="159"/>
and she was tall and strong. She had very high <lb/>
spirits and was always full of fun and ready to see <lb/>
the funny side of people and things. Her laughter <lb/>
and her happy voice, singing as she went about the <lb/>
house, were the delight of her father, who called her his <lb/>
sunshine. But though she loved her home and her <lb/>
rides and walks on the moors, she did not find there <lb/>
enough occupation for her active nature. Her mother <lb/>
died after a long time of ill-health, during which Dora <lb/>
had been one of her devoted nurses, and now Dora <lb/>
longed for some real work. Her father did not wish <lb/>
her to leave home, but he did not forbid it, and at last <lb/>
when she was twenty-nine, Dora went to be <reg orig="school-|mistress">schoolmistress</reg> <lb/>
at Woolston, a little village in <reg orig="Buckingham-|shire">Buckinghamshire</reg>. <lb/>
She lived there alone in a tiny cottage, loving <lb/>
the children who came to her school, and making herself <lb/>
the friend of all the poor and sick in the village. She <lb/>
did not feel, however, that this was her real work; and <lb/>
after three years she decided to join the Sisterhood of <lb/>
the Good Samaritans. She had learnt to know these <lb/>
Sisters in Yorkshire, as they had their chief home at <lb/>
Coatham, which was not very far from her old home. <lb/>
The Sisters had a Convalescent Home under their care, <lb/>
and many of them went out from Coatham to work in <lb/>
other towns.</p>
<p>After she joined the Sisterhood, Sister Dora, as she <lb/>
was now called, had to work very hard. The Sisters <lb/>
did all the work of the house, and Sister Dora cleaned <lb/>
floors and grates, swept and dusted, and for a time <lb/>
acted as cook. She sometimes felt it very hard to <lb/>
have to do all this work. Once when a gentleman <lb/>
whom she knew came into the kitchen where she was <lb/>
peeling potatoes, she pulled her hood over her face so <lb/>
that he might not see her. In after life she found the <lb/>
<pb n="160"/>
great advantage of having learnt how to do all the <lb/>
work of a house herself. She thought some of the <lb/>
rules very strict; but still she was very happy there, <lb/>
and the Sisters loved her. She was able also to learn <lb/>
more about nursing, as the Sisters had a Cottage <lb/>
Hospital near Middlesborough, to which she was sent. <lb/>
Sometimes, too, she was sent to nurse private patients, <lb/>
and sometimes to nurse in another Cottage Hospital <lb/>
for accidents at Walsall, which was managed by the <lb/>
Coatham Sisters.</p>
<p>At last Sister Dora settled altogether at Walsall, in <lb/>
charge of the little hospital there. Walsall is a great <lb/>
manufacturing centre, with coal pits, blast furnaces, and <lb/>
many kinds of factories. It had then no large hospital; <lb/>
the little Cottage Hospital was chiefly intended for <lb/>
accidents, and the patients were for the most part men <lb/>
and boys from the pits and workshops. There were <lb/>
also a large number of out-patients, men, women, and <lb/>
children. As most of the cases were accidents, Sister <lb/>
Dora was particularly anxious to become a good surgical <lb/>
nurse, and the chief surgeon at the hospital, when he <lb/>
saw how quick and clever she was, taught her all that <lb/>
he could, so that she could attend to many cases herself <lb/>
without the help of the doctor. The hospital in which <lb/>
she at first nursed was very small and inconvenient, <lb/>
with only fourteen beds, but a few years after Sister <lb/>
Dora settled in Walsall a new hospital was built on the <lb/>
top of the hill on which the town lies. It had <reg orig="twenty-|eight">twenty-eight</reg> <lb/>
beds, conveniently arranged in three wards, so <lb/>
that it was just possible for an active woman like Sister <lb/>
Dora to do all the nursing herself. She had the help <lb/>
of an old servant of her family, who came to live with <lb/>
her and who soon learnt to be a very capable nurse <lb/>
herself. Other women were engaged to sit up at night <lb/>
<pb n="161"/>
with the patients, and, later, Sister Dora used to have <lb/>
lady pupils who learnt nursing under her.</p>
<p>It was a very hard life, full of ceaseless work and <lb/>
responsibility, but Sister Dora threw her whole heart <lb/>
into it, and loved her work and the people for whom <lb/>
she worked. Once settled at Walsall, she never wished <lb/>
to leave it. Speaking to a friend about her work, she <lb/>
said, "I generally find that the more I have to do the <lb/>
stronger and happier I feel. It is hard enough <reg orig="some-|times">sometimes</reg> <lb/>
at night, when I have been round to all the <lb/>
patients and left them comfortable and asleep, and am <lb/>
just going to bed myself, to be called down by the bell, <lb/>
or perhaps roused by it just as I am falling asleep. <lb/>
But then I think 'the Master calleth thee,' and jump <lb/>
up and go down, to find perhaps some poor drunken <lb/>
man or woman, and it is difficult to recognise the <lb/>
Master in such poor degraded creatures as come to be <lb/>
doctored up." She had a wonderful power over the <lb/>
men and boys amongst whom she worked. She <reg orig="sym-|pathised">sympathised</reg> <lb/>
deeply with all their pain and trouble, and <lb/>
made them feel as if their troubles were her own, but <lb/>
she tried to make them forget their pain by her bright <lb/>
talk and her laughter and jokes. She would raise their <lb/>
spirits by her delightful fun, till an Irishman said once, <lb/>
"Make you laugh! she'd make you laugh when you <lb/>
were dying." Whenever she had a spare minute, she <lb/>
would read to them or talk to them or play games with <lb/>
them. She allowed no bad talk or quarrelling in the <lb/>
wards, and tried to mend her patients' morals as well as <lb/>
their limbs. They each of them knew that they had a <lb/>
real friend in her, and that she prayed for each and <lb/>
cared deeply what became of them. They loved to <lb/>
come and see her after they had left the hospital, and <lb/>
were always sure of a welcome. She tried hard to cure <lb/>
<pb n="162"/>
them from their drinking ways, showing them again <lb/>
and again how hard it was to heal the wounds of those <lb/>
who drank; and when they were brought in at night <lb/>
wounded after a drunken brawl, after dressing their <lb/>
wounds with all her usual gentleness, she would ask <lb/>
them why they did not behave like respectable members <lb/>
of society, instead of fighting in the streets and getting <lb/>
her up at unearthly hours of the night to mend their <lb/>
broken heads.</p>
<p>Sister Dora was devoted to children and they loved <lb/>
her, and she knew how to get them to bear patiently <lb/>
the dressing of their wounds. Often when a child was <lb/>
miserable and in pain, she would carry it about with <lb/>
her on one arm as she went through the wards, saying, <lb/>
"Don't you cry, Sister's got you," whilst with her other <lb/>
hand she attended to the patients. Many children <lb/>
suffering from terrible burns used to be brought to <lb/>
the hospital, and she grew so clever in treating them <lb/>
that the surgeons trusted them entirely to her care. <lb/>
Once a child was brought in so badly burnt that it <lb/>
was plain it had only a few hours to live. All pain <lb/>
had ceased, but the child was terrified. Sister Dora <lb/>
gave up all other work in order to comfort her. She <lb/>
sat by the bed for some hours talking to her about <lb/>
Jesus Christ and His love for little children, and about <lb/>
heaven where she would never feel hunger and pain <lb/>
again. The child grew peaceful and happy, and her <lb/>
last words were, "When you come to heaven, Sister, <lb/>
I'll meet you at the gates with a bunch of flowers."</p>
<p>Sister Dora felt special sympathy for the men who <lb/>
had been so hurt that it seemed necessary for them <lb/>
to have an arm or leg cut off. She knew well how <lb/>
difficult this made it for them to earn a livelihood, and <lb/>
she devoted all her skill to saving the wounded limb <lb/>
<pb n="163"/>
if possible. One night a fine healthy young man was <lb/>
brought in with his arm torn and twisted by a machine. <lb/>
The doctor said that nothing could save it, and that <lb/>
he must cut it off at once. Sister Dora was moved <lb/>
by the despair of the poor man; she looked long at <lb/>
his arm and at himself, and the man cried out, "O <lb/>
Sister! save my arm for me; it's my right arm." When <lb/>
she turned to the doctor and asked if she might try <lb/>
to save the arm, he only asked her if she was mad, and <lb/>
said that the man's life could not be saved unless his <lb/>
arm were taken off at once. But she turned to the <lb/>
patient and said, "Are you willing for me to try to <lb/>
save your arm, my man?" He was willing, but the <lb/>
surgeon was very angry, and refused to help her, saying, <lb/>
"Remember, it's your arm," and telling her she must <lb/>
take all the responsibility. Night and day for three <lb/>
weeks she tended him, naturally feeling terribly anxious <lb/>
as to what would happen. She often said afterwards, <lb/>
"How I prayed over that arm." At the end of that <lb/>
time she asked the surgeon to come and look at her <lb/>
work, and when she unbandaged the arm and showed <lb/>
it to him, straightened and in a healthy, promising <lb/>
condition, he exclaimed, "Why you have saved it, and <lb/>
it will be a useful arm to him for many a long year." <lb/>
It is not surprising that Sister Dora wept with joy at <lb/>
her success, nor that the man became one of her <lb/>
most devoted admirers. He was nicknamed "Sister's <lb/>
Arm" in the hospital, and used to come back often <lb/>
to see her after he had left.</p>
<p>Another man himself tells how she had to persuade <lb/>
him to allow his leg to be taken off as the only way of <lb/>
saving his life. He had grown so thin and wasted that <lb/>
she used to carry him upstairs in her arms so that he <lb/>
might join in the prayers she held for the whole <lb/>
<pb n="164"/>
hospital. He was eight months in the hospital, and he <lb/>
says, "I learned to love Sister Dora as a mother." He <lb/>
tells how she used in the afternoons to attend to the <lb/>
out-patients, "dress their wounds, set a broken arm, <lb/>
sew up a cut, or draw teeth, in fact anything that was <lb/>
required of her she would do, and always with the <lb/>
tenderest care and the kindest word to all." She often <lb/>
amused the men with tales of her doings in the country <lb/>
as a girl, and told them about her riding and <reg orig="fox-|hunting">fox-hunting</reg>, <lb/>
and this man who watched her life in the <lb/>
hospital for eight months says, "those patients who <lb/>
were the most trouble, she seemed the fondest of." She <lb/>
knew how to get the men to help her by making them <lb/>
wait upon one another; generally there was some boy <lb/>
who had to stay a long while in the hospital, who <lb/>
waited upon her as a devoted slave. After she had <lb/>
been four years at the hospital, to show their gratitude <lb/>
for all she had done, her patients subscribed fifty <lb/>
pounds amongst themselves with which they bought a <lb/>
small carriage and pony for her. She delighted in <lb/>
using it to send convalescents for a drive, and found it <lb/>
a help in taking her to visit sick people in their homes. <lb/>
She seldom took a holiday herself, and once was three <lb/>
years at the hospital without any break, but if she <lb/>
did go away into the country with friends, she <reg orig="en-|joyed">enjoyed</reg> <lb/>
everything with all her old energy, bathing or <lb/>
skating, taking long walks, when she would lead the <lb/>
way in scaling fences or fording streams. Sometimes <lb/>
she took patients who were convalescent for <reg orig="expedi-|tions">expeditions</reg> <lb/>
into the country or to visit Lichfield Cathedral. <lb/>
The old patients specially loved to revisit the hospital <lb/>
on Sundays, when, after a clergyman had held a short <lb/>
service, Sister Dora used to speak to them herself, <lb/>
and then lead them in the singing of many hymns.</p>
<pb n="165"/>
<p>She always had a small Bible in her pocket, and <lb/>
studied it whenever she had a spare minute.</p>
<p>In 1875 there was a terrible outbreak of smallpox in <lb/>
Walsall. There was an isolation hospital on the <reg orig="out-|skirts">outskirts</reg> <lb/>
of the town, but in those days people were not <lb/>
compelled by law to send smallpox patients away, and <lb/>
they refused to go of their own accord, for they said <lb/>
that they would rather die at home. It was very <lb/>
necessary for the welfare of the town that they should <lb/>
be persuaded to go to the hospital and not spread the <lb/>
terrible infection by staying in their own homes. So <lb/>
Sister Dora offered to leave her hospital and go to <lb/>
take charge of the Smallpox Hospital. She knew that <lb/>
the people trusted her, and thought that they would <lb/>
come if she was there. Her offer was gladly accepted; <lb/>
all through the town the news ran, "Sister is going to <lb/>
the Epidemic Hospital." Her lady pupils were left <lb/>
to take charge of the hospital, and she went off to her <lb/>
lonely work with the surgeon of the hospital to show <lb/>
her the way. It seemed such a lonely and desolate <lb/>
spot that even her courage failed her at the door, and <lb/>
she cried out, "Oh take me back, I cannot endure this <lb/>
dreadful place." But the surgeon knew her real courage, <lb/>
and only said, "Come in." It was an admirably <lb/>
planned little hospital, and she was delighted with it. <lb/>
There were twenty-eight beds, and she had not been <lb/>
half-an-hour in the hospital before seven patients <lb/>
arrived, to be followed by many more. Her only <lb/>
regular helper was the porter, an old man, who did all <lb/>
he could for her when he was sober, but used sometimes <lb/>
to go away and get drunk, leaving her alone for the <lb/>
whole night. Two old women came in from the <lb/>
workhouse to help her in washing the clothes and <lb/>
bedding, but much of the scrubbing and cleaning she <lb/>
<pb n="166"/>
had to do herself, as well as all the nursing. One of <lb/>
the police who came to see her told her that the people <lb/>
in the town declared they should not mind having <lb/>
the smallpox with "Sister" to nurse them. Some few <lb/>
people were brave enough to visit her in her loneliness, <lb/>
and to bring her books and flowers and news of her <lb/>
patients at the hospital.</p>
<p>One of the old patients, an engine-stoker, went often <lb/>
to see her after his day's work was done. He had been <lb/>
twice in the hospital under her care, and he said, "I <lb/>
could not tell you all her goodness to me, words would <lb/>
fail me if I tried." She was full of courage and joy in <lb/>
her work, and wrote to a friend: "You must not fret. <lb/>
I rejoice that He has permitted one so unworthy to <lb/>
work for Him; and oh, if He should think me fit to lay <lb/>
down my life for Him, rejoice, rejoice, at so great a <lb/>
privilege." Even her sense of fun did not leave her, <lb/>
and she wrote a long letter to her old patients at the <lb/>
Cottage Hospital, calling them all by their nicknames <lb/>
and sending messages to each. She said of a boy who <lb/>
was her special slave: "What shall I say to my beloved <lb/>
Sam. I wish I had my boy here. I send him twenty <lb/>
kisses and hope he has been in church to-day and in <lb/>
time. He must not sulk all the time I am away. I <lb/>
have two blessed babies, who alternately keep up music <lb/>
all day and night, accompanied by an Irishwoman's <lb/>
tongue, so I am not dull. Have you been singing <reg orig="to-|day">today</reg>? <lb/>
You must sing particularly, 'Safe in the arms <lb/>
of Jesus' and think of me. Living or dying, I am <lb/>
His. Oh, my children, you all love me for the very <lb/>
little I do for you; but oh, if you would only think <lb/>
what Jesus has done, and is doing for you, your hearts <lb/>
would soon be full of love for Him, and you would all <lb/>
choose Him for your Master."</p>
<pb n="167"/>
<p>Towards the middle of May, the Smallpox Hospital <lb/>
was empty and she hoped soon to leave; but before she <lb/>
was ready to go new patients were brought in, and this <lb/>
happened several times, so that it was not till the <lb/>
middle of August, after six months' work at the <reg orig="Small-|pox">Smallpox</reg> <lb/>
Hospital, that she was able to close it.</p>
<p>The following October a terrible explosion occurred <lb/>
at the furnace of some ironworks, and eleven men were <lb/>
covered with streams of molten metal. In their agony <lb/>
they jumped into a neighbouring canal, and were with <lb/>
difficulty rescued and taken in cabs to the hospital. <lb/>
Burnt all over and frightfully disfigured, they were <lb/>
carried in and laid on the floor till a ward could be <lb/>
cleared for them. It was a terrible scene, even the <lb/>
doctors could hardly stay in the ward, but Sister Dora <lb/>
never ceased in her devoted care of the men. Cries <lb/>
came from most of them, "Sister, come and dress me." <lb/>
"Do dress me," "Oh, you don't know how bad I am." <lb/>
She could only answer, "Oh my poor men, I'll dress you <lb/>
all, if you'll give me time." One poor man, seeing how <lb/>
distracted she was by the different cries for help, said, <lb/>
"Sister Dora, I want to be dressed very bad, but if <lb/>
there's any wants you worse go and do them first." He <lb/>
was in terrible pain and died during the night. Of the <lb/>
eleven only two recovered. Some lingered for as long <lb/>
as ten days, and during that time Sister Dora never <lb/>
went to bed, and hardly left the ward. One of those <lb/>
who survived described how she went from bed to <lb/>
bed talking, laughing, even joking with the men; <lb/>
telling them stories, doing everything she could to <lb/>
distract them from their pain, and pointing out the <lb/>
way to heaven to those who were to die. He spoke <lb/>
with delight of her visits to his bedside at night when <lb/>
he was recovering, saying, "It did you good only to <lb/>
<pb n="168"/>
look at her," and ending with, "What we felt for her I <lb/>
couldn't tell you; my tongue won't say it."</p>
<p>One result of this terrible accident was that the ward <lb/>
in which the burnt men had lain was so poisoned that <lb/>
it could not be used again, and it was decided to build <lb/>
a new hospital. In the meanwhile, a house was fitted <lb/>
up as a temporary hospital. It was a tiring life for <lb/>
Sister Dora, as the temporary hospital was small and <lb/>
not at all convenient, and many patients had to be <lb/>
nursed in their own homes. It was at this time that <lb/>
she first began to find it difficult to lift her patients, <lb/>
and after a while she was compelled to consult a doctor <lb/>
about her health. He discovered that she had a mortal <lb/>
malady. It was possible that an operation might do <lb/>
her some good, but it was by no means certain. She <lb/>
determined to go on as usual, and made him promise to <lb/>
tell no one of her illness. She worked harder than <lb/>
ever and would not give in. She drove about in her <lb/>
little pony carriage to visit her patients, and no one <lb/>
was allowed to know that anything was wrong with her. <lb/>
Then an outbreak of fever in the temporary hospital <lb/>
made it necessary to close it, and as the new hospital <lb/>
was not yet ready it was possible for Sister Dora to <lb/>
leave Walsall. She visited her relations and went to <lb/>
Paris and London to study improvements in surgical <lb/>
science. All the time her disease was growing worse, <lb/>
and still she told no one. Her wish was to die at <lb/>
Walsall amongst her own people, and as the hospital <lb/>
was not ready, a little house near to it was taken for <lb/>
her. People could not believe that she was dying. She <lb/>
was surrounded with all the care that love could give <lb/>
her, and often her visitors were surprised to see her, in <lb/>
spite of pain and weakness, still her old self, full of fun <lb/>
and jokes. Her interest in the new hospital was very <lb/>
<pb n="169"/>
<figure id="f2" rend="page">
<head><hi rend="small-caps">The Statue at Walsall</hi></head>
</figure>
<pb n="170"/>
keen, and she rejoiced that it was finished in time for <lb/>
her to know of its opening. She listened eagerly to all <lb/>
that was told her about it, and gave her advice about <lb/>
all the arrangements. Often she suffered terribly, and <lb/>
when at last she died, on Christmas eve, 1878, it was <lb/>
with relief that her friends heard that her pain was <lb/>
over. She was carried to her grave by some of the <lb/>
railway men for whom she had cared with so much <lb/>
devotion. The Bishop was there and great numbers <lb/>
of the clergy, and there came, too, hundreds of her <lb/>
patients and an immense crowd consisting of nearly <lb/>
all the people of the town.</p>
<p>When, later, it was discussed what memorial of her <lb/>
should be placed in Walsall some suggested a <reg orig="Con-|valescent">Convalescent</reg> <lb/>
Home, as what she herself would most have <lb/>
desired; but the working men of the town were quite <lb/>
clear that what they wanted was a statue of Sister Dora. <lb/>
One of them said that of course they could not forget <lb/>
her, but that they wanted her to be there, so that when <lb/>
strangers came and saw the statue and asked who it <lb/>
was, they might answer, "Who's that? Why that's our <lb/>
Sister Dora." So her statue in her nurse's dress, as she <lb/>
lived and worked amongst them, stands in the centre <lb/>
of Walsall to remind the people of her life of love. <lb/>
The workmen spoke of her as "the most saintly thing <lb/>
that was ever given us."</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
