<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="UVA" rend="none"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="none"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOdia SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-dia.ent"> %ISOdia;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-tech.ent"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="UVA" rend="none">
<teiHeader type="migrated">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Foster_Heroines of Modern Religion</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl/></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2009-09-29">September 29, 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<name id="aec6v">Andrew Curley, University of Virginia Library</name>
<resp>corrector</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>Minor corrections to vendor markup.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="t1">
<body id="t1-body">
<div1 type="chapter" n="VI" id="d3">
<pb n="134"/>
<head>CHAPTER VI</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d4">
<head>SISTER DORA</head>
<byline>BY GERTRUDE LESLIE MUMFORD</byline>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">Occasionally</hi> in searching for the <reg orig="de-|velopment">development</reg> <lb/>
of great natures one finds that <lb/>
from their very faults, from the very <reg orig="tempera-|mental">temperamental</reg> <lb/>
obstacles against which they struggle, <lb/>
spring the sources of their greatness. So it <lb/>
was with Dorothy Wyndlow Pattison, with a <lb/>
will so strong that, although it often brought <lb/>
her into difficulties, it enabled her successfully <lb/>
to struggle through difficulties that would have <lb/>
overwhelmed a woman less determined. The <lb/>
very characteristic that sometimes became a <lb/>
stumbling block to her feet more often proved <lb/>
to be the means of the fulfillment of her <reg orig="as-|pirations">aspirations</reg>.</p>
<p>Dorothy Pattison, born January 16, 1832, in <lb/>
the little village of Hauxwell, near Richmond, <lb/>
in the North Riding of Yorkshire, was the <lb/>
eleventh child of a family of twelve. Her <lb/>
father was Reverend Mark James Pattison, a <lb/>
man who "walked with God." From him she <lb/>
inherited her shapely figure, while from her <lb/>
mother, the daughter of a Richmond banker, <lb/>
came her beauty of feature and coloring so <lb/>
much admired. As a child Dorothy was very <lb/>
<pb/>
<figure id="f1" rend="page">
<head>SISTER DORA</head>
</figure>
<pb/>
<pb n="135"/>
delicate&mdash;a fact that kept her from regular <lb/>
lessons.</p>
<p>Her knowledge she picked up in scraps which <lb/>
she eagerly stored away in her retentive mind. <lb/>
In her childhood, as in her later life, she was <lb/>
quick to grasp a situation; her powers of <reg orig="ob-|servation">observation</reg> <lb/>
later stood her in good stead in the <lb/>
hospital ward. Among the country people she <lb/>
had the reputation of being a quiet child but <lb/>
it was due to the fact that she was not <reg orig="suffi-|ciently">sufficiently</reg> <lb/>
robust to throw herself into active <lb/>
sports. Delicate or not, she was by nature <lb/>
both mischievous and strong-willed, the leader <lb/>
in many escapades.</p>
<p>Upon one occasion she and one of her sisters <lb/>
had new Sunday bonnets which they did not <lb/>
like. In vain they pleaded not to wear them; <lb/>
the decree had gone forth that the <reg orig="bon-|nets">bonnets</reg> <lb/>
must be worn out. At last Dorothy's <lb/>
chance appeared in a pouring rainstorm which <lb/>
came up one day when Mr. and Mrs. Pattison <lb/>
were out. "Quick!" cried Dorothy to her <reg orig="sis-|ter">sister</reg>, <lb/>
"here is our chance for getting rid of the <lb/>
bonnets." On went the bonnets, and the <reg orig="chil-|dren's">children's</reg> <lb/>
heads were thrust out of the window <lb/>
until the distasteful headgear was completely <lb/>
ruined. When Sunday came, the two children <lb/>
appeared with no bonnets. Upon being sent <lb/>
for them they returned, confident and cheerful, <lb/>
with the wrecks upon their heads. "Why, <lb/>
mamma, we can't wear those," said Dorothy. <lb/>
But they did, not only for that day but for <lb/>
many a day afterwards!</p>
<pb n="136"/>
<p>In the parish, she was a general favorite. <lb/>
The Pattisons, as a family, were both <reg orig="chari-|table">charitable</reg> <lb/>
and hospitable towards their poor <reg orig="neigh-|bors">neighbors</reg>, <lb/>
and Dorothy shared with her sisters the <lb/>
work of carrying aid to the cottagers. The <lb/>
girls saved their pocket money and turned and <lb/>
remade their old dresses so that by spending <lb/>
less for clothes they might have more money <lb/>
to give. Sometimes when they were seated at <lb/>
the dinner table with the keen appetities of <reg orig="nor-|mal">normal</reg> <lb/>
children after a morning in the open air, a <lb/>
remark of the rector that poor So-and-So must <lb/>
be faring badly as Bill was out of work again <lb/>
would cause them to pack their own hearty <reg orig="din-|ner">dinner</reg> <lb/>
in a basket and take it to the suffering <lb/>
family, while they themselves dined on bread <lb/>
and cheese. They delighted to give, not only <lb/>
material things, but their time and practical <lb/>
sympathy. Once, when Dorothy was abroad, <lb/>
a schoolboy in the village became very sick <lb/>
with rheumatic fever. His one longing was to <lb/>
live to see "Miss Dora" again. On the day on <lb/>
which she returned he listened intently and long <lb/>
before anyone else could hear the carriage <lb/>
wheels he cried, "There she is," and waited <lb/>
with what patience he could command. He <lb/>
was not disappointed; at once she became his <lb/>
nurse and remained with him until he died.</p>
<p>As she grew older she outgrew the delicacy <lb/>
that had characterized her as a child, and with <lb/>
her newly-acquired strength she felt the need <lb/>
of action. Outdoor games and driving but most <lb/>
of all vigorous cross-country riding, she made <lb/>
<pb n="137"/>
an outlet for her overflowing energy. She <reg orig="be-|came">became</reg> <lb/>
a daring rider, followed the hounds with <lb/>
keen enjoyment, and cantered alone across the <lb/>
solitary moors.</p>
<p>At twenty, she was a picture of health, with <lb/>
a personal beauty that was obvious to the <reg orig="dull-|est">dullest</reg> <lb/>
eye. As she came back from a <reg orig="cross-coun-|try">cross-country</reg> <lb/>
gallop, with brown curls loosened, and the <lb/>
delicate color of her cheeks heightened by the <lb/>
sharp country wind, she was a picture at which <lb/>
all turned to look. To physical strength and <lb/>
beauty were united high animal spirits and a <lb/>
sense of humor, which, always sparkling out <lb/>
through her merry brown eyes, were to keep <lb/>
her sweet and strong through the trials of the <lb/>
years before her.</p>
<p>But the energy that caused her, when <reg orig="phys-|ically">physically</reg> <lb/>
able, as a child to tear vigorously <lb/>
through the house in strenuous games with her <lb/>
brothers and sisters, and, later, to enjoy so <lb/>
much a wild gallop upon a horse's back, now <lb/>
demanded some definite work upon which to <lb/>
spend its powers. A passive acceptance of life <lb/>
was foreign to her nature. She longed to be <lb/>
out and doing. Florence Nightingale's<ref target="n137.1" n="1">*</ref>
<note id="n137.1" place="foot" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p>See Chapter V, page 120, <hi rend="italic">Heroines of Modern Progress.</hi></p></note>
 work <lb/>
in the Crimean war roused all her enthusiasm. <lb/>
She begged her father to let her go out to <lb/>
Scutari as a nurse, but upon his refusal she <lb/>
acquiesced with outward quietness. She <lb/>
slighted none of her duties, in the home or in <lb/>
the village, and spent much of her time in <reg orig="nurs-|ing">nursing</reg> <lb/>
her invalid mother. Sometimes she visited <lb/>
<pb n="138"/>
her oldest brother, Mark, at Redcar. When <lb/>
she was twenty-nine, her mother died, and thus <lb/>
Dorothy's chief work in the home was taken <lb/>
away from her.</p>
<p>At Choatham, near Redcar where she visited <lb/>
her brother, was an order of nursing sisters&mdash; <lb/>
the Sisterhood of the Good Samaritans. There <lb/>
they had established a convalescent hospital, <lb/>
and they devoted themselves to relieving the <lb/>
sickness of the poor of that neighborhood. In <lb/>
their example, Dorothy thought she had found <lb/>
the solution for her unsatisfied craving for a <lb/>
life of worth-while activity. Her father, <reg orig="how-|ever">however</reg>, <lb/>
was opposed to the idea of her entering <lb/>
the sisterhood; so for the time she gave it up. <lb/>
But she could not longer remain idle in <reg orig="com-|fort">comfort</reg>. <lb/>
Just at this time she saw an <reg orig="advertise-|ment">advertisement</reg> <lb/>
for a lady to take charge of the village <lb/>
school at Little Woolston, on the borders of <lb/>
Buckinghamshire, and in October, 1861, much <lb/>
against the wishes of her father, she left home <lb/>
to become a teacher.</p>
<p>Here she threw herself into the labors of a <lb/>
parish schoolmistress, but far in excess of her <lb/>
duties. She not only taught the children, but <lb/>
she visited them in their homes, nursed them <lb/>
when they were sick, played with them when <lb/>
they were well, told them wonderful stories, <lb/>
and in return was fervently loved by them. <lb/>
Nor did she stop there; her work extended to <lb/>
the poor and sick of the whole parish. If she <lb/>
was lonely, living by herself in a tiny cottage <lb/>
with no servant except an old woman who came <lb/>
<pb n="139"/>
in occasionally to scrub, she only threw herself <lb/>
harder into the work. Indeed, she probably <lb/>
overworked, and a neglected cold soon brought <lb/>
on an attack of pleurisy. When she grew a <lb/>
little better she was sent to Redcar to <reg orig="con-|valesce">convalesce</reg>; <lb/>
the associations there roused in her <lb/>
all the longings for a definite and settled life <lb/>
work&mdash;longings that had been steadily growing <lb/>
within her. This time her willfulness would <lb/>
brook no opposition; against the combined <lb/>
wishes of the members of her family, in the <lb/>
autumn of 1864, she became a sister of the <reg orig="or-|der">order</reg> <lb/>
of the Good Samaritans.</p>
<p>The Sisterhood of the Good Samaritans is <lb/>
what is termed a "secular" order affiliated with <lb/>
the Church of England. That is, it is a <reg orig="work-|ing">working</reg> <lb/>
order whose members are bound by no <lb/>
vows except one of a definite term of obedience <lb/>
to their pastor and to the "mother superior" <lb/>
appointed by him. To this order, then, <lb/>
Dorothy Pattison, henceforth Sister Dora, <lb/>
brought her burning ardor for work. Here she <lb/>
was put through a severe training, which, while <lb/>
distasteful to her at the time, undoubtedly not <lb/>
only made her proficient in the mechanical part <lb/>
of her profession but gave her lessons in <reg orig="self-|control">self-control</reg>. <lb/>
She learned to make beds and to <lb/>
cook; at first, when those in charge pulled to <lb/>
pieces the beds she had just made, she would <lb/>
sit down and cry for discouragement, but in the <lb/>
end her good sense conquered and she quickly <lb/>
learned to adopt the approved methods. A <lb/>
large part of her time was spent in a small <lb/>
<pb n="140"/>
cottage hospital in North Ormesbury, where <lb/>
she worked sometimes with another sister but <lb/>
often alone. On January 5, 1865, she writes <lb/>
from Ormesbury to a friend in Little <reg orig="Wools-|ton">Woolston</reg>: <lb/>
"I have been ordered off to the hospital <lb/>
to-day, and am sitting up to-night with a poor <lb/>
man who is suffering from concussion of the <lb/>
brain; and he alarms me by getting up and <lb/>
trying to get away, and he is insensible [<hi rend="italic">i. e</hi>. not <lb/>
himself], so that it is useless speaking to him. <lb/>
It is so cold that, though sitting over the fire, <lb/>
I am shivering. I have put a blister on my <lb/>
patient. I hope, when it takes effect, there will <lb/>
be an improvement. I hope he won't die, for <lb/>
I am the only Sister here; the others have gone <lb/>
for their holiday."</p>
<p>She stayed at North Ormesbury until the <lb/>
early part of 1865, when she was sent to <reg orig="Wal-|sall">Walsall</reg>, <lb/>
in South Staffordshire, to assist in the <lb/>
work of a small cottage hospital there.</p>
<p>Walsall is an industrial town in the coal and <lb/>
iron district near Birmingham, on the outskirts <lb/>
of the "Black Country." By day it is <reg orig="sor-|did">sordid</reg> <lb/>
and dingy, but at night it glows with an <lb/>
awful splendor. The same smelting furnaces <lb/>
whose smoke daily blackens the landscape, at <lb/>
night glare through the darkness with a <reg orig="malig-|nant">malignant</reg> <lb/>
flaming red positively infernal. The <lb/>
smelting furnaces and the coalpits furnished <lb/>
work for most of the men in town. Accidents <lb/>
were numerous and medical aid was scarce; a <lb/>
hospital of some sort where the wounded <lb/>
could be taken for immediate treatment became <lb/>
<pb n="141"/>
a necessity. Accordingly, in 1863, a cottage <lb/>
hospital of four beds was established under <lb/>
the charge of Sister Mary of the Good <reg orig="Samari-|tans">Samaritans</reg>. <lb/>
By the time it was a year old the number <lb/>
of beds had increased to fourteen. Hither, <lb/>
in 1865, Sister Mary having fallen ill, came <lb/>
Sister Dora, as head of the hospital. <reg orig="Imme-|diately">Immediately</reg> <lb/>
after her arrival she caught smallpox <lb/>
from some of the outpatients and for a <lb/>
time was very ill. She was put in a small room <lb/>
whose window faced the street. At that time <lb/>
the little hospital was the victim of much <lb/>
opposition and even petty persecution from the <lb/>
very people it was there to help. Stones and <lb/>
mud were thrown at the window of the room <lb/>
where Sister Dora lay sick. Soon after her <reg orig="re-|covery">recovery</reg>, <lb/>
as she passed a crowd of roughs, <lb/>
one exclaimed: "There goes one of those <lb/>
Sisters of <hi rend="italic">Misery</hi>!" At the same time he <lb/>
threw a stone which cut her forehead. A <lb/>
short time later, the very fellow was badly <lb/>
hurt in a coalpit accident and was brought to <lb/>
the hospital, where Sister Dora nursed him <lb/>
with particular care. One day, when he had <lb/>
nearly recovered, she discovered him silently <lb/>
crying, and presently he penitently blurted out <lb/>
the whole story. To his surprise, he learned <lb/>
that Sister Dora had recognized him when he <lb/>
was brought in. This was his first experience <lb/>
with the Christian ideal of returning good for <lb/>
evil.</p>
<p>In April 1865, she was recalled to Choatham <lb/>
for a short time. Here the restraint and <reg orig="de-|corum">decorum</reg> <lb/>
<pb n="142"/>
imposed by the Sisterhood sometimes <lb/>
proved too much for her lively spirits. One <lb/>
day a donkey with the reputation of upsetting <lb/>
everybody was brought to the door of the <lb/>
home. "Oh, let me ride him," cried Sister <lb/>
Dora. "He won't kick me off." Tying her <lb/>
bonnet strings a little more tightly than usual, <lb/>
with her black skirts tucked up carefully around <lb/>
her, she mounted the beast and managed to <lb/>
stick for a while despite his most frantic <lb/>
efforts to throw her. It was a clash of two <lb/>
stubborn wills, but the brute strength of the <lb/>
donkey finally won and Sister Dora in spite of <lb/>
her proud boast was ignominiously thrown. <lb/>
She did penance for this prank, however, <reg orig="be-|cause">because</reg> <lb/>
for some days her knees were so bruised <lb/>
and swollen that they were very painful to kneel <lb/>
on. She had had her fun, however, and bore <lb/>
the pain in silence rather than confess her <reg orig="un-|dignified">undignified</reg> <lb/>
behavior to the mother superior.</p>
<p>It must not be supposed that her <reg orig="irrepress-|ible">irrepressible</reg> <lb/>
spirits were always thus in evidence. <lb/>
Just before coming to Walsall she had passed <lb/>
through the crisis of her religious life. She <lb/>
had never lost her sense of the nearness of God <lb/>
and a firm belief in the efficacy of prayer, but <lb/>
her intellectual judgment had become distorted. <lb/>
For a time her intelligence balked at believing <lb/>
the authenticity of the Scriptures and her <reg orig="at-|titude">attitude</reg> <lb/>
might well have been summed up "Lord, <lb/>
I believe; help Thou my unbelief." During <lb/>
this time she was aided and strengthened by <lb/>
Reverend Richard Twigg, rector of St. John's, <lb/>
<pb n="143"/>
Wednesbury, to whose church for early <reg orig="com-|munion">communion</reg> <lb/>
she walked almost every Sunday <reg orig="morn-|ing">morning</reg>. <lb/>
Large-hearted, large-minded, his life <lb/>
a living example of his faith, he steadied <lb/>
and held Sister Dora as no one else could. <lb/>
Among all the people she met during her stay <lb/>
in Walsall, Mr. Twigg was the one who, more <lb/>
than anyone else, was destined to help her most <lb/>
when she needed help. She emerged from this <lb/>
inner trial, however, with her whole being <reg orig="cen-|tered">centered</reg> <lb/>
around a deep personal love of her <lb/>
Saviour, Jesus Christ. Later she was to be <lb/>
tested and it was this sincere devotion to her <lb/>
Lord that brought her out triumphant.</p>
<p>Her always strong desire to help others was <lb/>
re&euml;nforced by the inward peace and sense of <lb/>
love she now felt. She had inherited a <reg orig="com-|paratively">comparatively</reg> <lb/>
large income but she spent it chiefly <lb/>
on others; her own wants were very simple. <lb/>
Work and prayer seemed to be the two rules <lb/>
of her life and it would be hard to say which <lb/>
predominated.</p>
<p>It was this spirit that she carried with her <lb/>
back to Walsall after her second brief stay at <lb/>
Choatham. There she took up her work again <lb/>
quietly and unobtrusively. For a long time <lb/>
the prosperous and healthy hardly knew of <lb/>
her. Only in the slums, in the back allies where <lb/>
ignorance and dirt fought a winning fight <lb/>
against health, she was known by those whom <lb/>
she sought out&mdash;those so miserable that they <lb/>
would not, even for relief, obtrude themselves <lb/>
at the hospital. It is no wonder that they <lb/>
<pb n="144"/>
learned to love her who healed their bodies <lb/>
even as she prayed for their souls. So she <lb/>
moved in and out among them, in all kinds of <lb/>
weather, at all hours, never considering <reg orig="her-|self&mdash;indeed">herself&mdash;indeed</reg> <lb/>
throwing herself into her work <lb/>
with such impetuous eagerness that in 1866 she <lb/>
had a serious illness; for three weeks her life <lb/>
was in danger. Then the people of Walsall <lb/>
found out what Sister Dora meant to the <lb/>
town. The hospital was besieged with <reg orig="in-|quiries">inquiries</reg>, <lb/>
and she herself always felt that her <lb/>
recovery was due to the prayers of the <reg orig="con-|gregation">congregation</reg> <lb/>
of St. John's, Wednesbury, where <lb/>
she attended church.</p>
<p>The usefulness of the hospital increased <lb/>
steadily, and under her adequate care, gave <lb/>
great relief to the community. The small, <lb/>
fourteen-bed building soon proved to be <reg orig="insuffi-|cient">insufficient</reg>. <lb/>
Always poorly ventilated, it became so <lb/>
impregnated with infection that wounds refused <lb/>
to heal, and case after case was sent away <reg orig="un-|cured">uncured</reg>. <lb/>
The committee in charge resolved to <lb/>
build one larger and better. In this <reg orig="under-|taking">undertaking</reg> <lb/>
they not only had Sister Dora's approval <lb/>
but, to a great extent, her financial aid, and <lb/>
thanks to her assistance the new hospital was <lb/>
ready for occupancy in 1868. It was situated <lb/>
on a hill, with good ventilation, and had <reg orig="twenty-|eight">twenty-eight</reg> <lb/>
beds with room for more if needed. Just <lb/>
as patients and nurses were well settled in their <lb/>
new quarters, a smallpox epidemic broke out. <lb/>
Sister Dora's efforts were now redoubled. <lb/>
Every minute that she could spare from her <lb/>
<pb n="145"/>
hospital duties she spent nursing the victims <lb/>
in their homes. Often she would be the only <lb/>
one in the house besides the sick person. One <lb/>
night she found a man dying with "blackpox" <lb/>
&mdash;smallpox in its most virulent form. There <lb/>
was no light in the house but a small <reg orig="candle-|end">candle-end</reg>; <lb/>
so giving a neighbor some money she <lb/>
asked her to get a light of some sort. The <lb/>
woman did not come back; as the miserable bit <lb/>
of candle flickered down, the dying man raised <lb/>
himself, saying: "Sister, do not leave me <reg orig="be-|fore">before</reg> <lb/>
I die." She took him in her arms, and in <lb/>
total darkness she sat on through the long night <lb/>
even after he had died, until the dawn came.</p>
<p>In course of time the epidemic was over, and <lb/>
work settled down to its accustomed routine. <lb/>
From the beginning of her hospital career <reg orig="Sis-|ter">Sister</reg> <lb/>
Dora had determined to become an efficient <lb/>
surgical nurse. The old surgeon of the <reg orig="hos-|pital">hospital</reg>, <lb/>
seeing her cool and sensible courage, had <lb/>
taught her as much as he could. She <reg orig="under-|took">undertook</reg> <lb/>
more and more of the minor cases and <lb/>
gradually came to set all the fractures. She <lb/>
was an advocate of conservative surgery and <lb/>
invariably voted against amputation if there <lb/>
seemed even a chance of saving the limb. One <lb/>
night a young man was brought in whose arm <lb/>
had been caught in his machine and so badly <lb/>
torn and twisted that the physician declared it <lb/>
must be amputated immediately. Sister Dora's <lb/>
sympathy was aroused by the young fellow's <lb/>
groan of despair. He turned from the doctor <lb/>
to her kindly face and implored her to save <lb/>
<pb n="146"/>
him. She examined the wound attentively; <lb/>
the young workman's face showed that he had <lb/>
led a clean and wholesome life. She told the <lb/>
doctor she thought she could save the arm. <lb/>
He replied flatly that amputation was <reg orig="neces-|sary">necessary</reg>, <lb/>
and refused to have another thing to do <lb/>
with the case. On her own responsibility, <reg orig="Sis-|ter">Sister</reg> <lb/>
Dora undertook to save the arm. After <lb/>
three weeks of tense anxiety on her part, she <lb/>
called the physician and showed him the arm <lb/>
progressing rapidly towards its old time <reg orig="use-|fulness">usefulness</reg>. <lb/>
With pride the surgeon who had <lb/>
taught her brought the hospital staff to show <lb/>
them what might be done. The patient <reg orig="there-|after">thereafter</reg> <lb/>
went by the name of "Sister's Arm."</p>
<p>Sister Dora had been doing all the nursing, <lb/>
the wardwork, and sometimes even the <reg orig="cook-|ing">cooking</reg>, <lb/>
but the work had increased so much that <lb/>
she was now obliged to have help. <reg orig="Accord-|ingly">Accordingly</reg>, <lb/>
with the consent of the committee, she <lb/>
took a small number of "lady-pupils" to teach <lb/>
the rudiments of nursing. As a teacher she <lb/>
was not wholly successful; she was rather <reg orig="im-|patient">impatient</reg>, <lb/>
preferring to do the task herself than <lb/>
to go through the tedious process of showing <lb/>
others how to do it. The difficulty was that <lb/>
she did not have the power of organizing the <lb/>
efforts of others, and her own personality was <lb/>
so great that it had overshadowed all lesser <lb/>
endeavors. "The main lesson which her <reg orig="lady-|pupils">ladypupils</reg> <lb/>
carried away from Walsall, was not how <lb/>
to dress wounds or how to bandage, or even <lb/>
how to manage a hospital on the most popular <lb/>
<pb n="147"/>
as well as on the most economical method, but <lb/>
rather the mighty results which the motive <lb/>
power of love towards God, and for His sake, <lb/>
towards mankind, might enable one single <lb/>
woman to effect."</p>
<p>A great deal of her work was done for <reg orig="chil-|dren">children</reg>, <lb/>
with whom she was an especial favorite. <lb/>
Often she would carry the littlest one around <lb/>
on one arm, while she made beds, prepared <lb/>
medicine, or did other hospital work. To the <lb/>
fretful she would say, "Don't you cry; Sister's <lb/>
got you!" Burns were perhaps the <reg orig="common-|est">commonest</reg> <lb/>
cases which the hospital had to treat. <reg orig="Chil-|dren">Children</reg> <lb/>
were brought almost frantic with terror <lb/>
and pain. When such a case came in, she would <lb/>
drop whatever work was in hand and bend all <lb/>
her energies to soothing the frightened child. <lb/>
After she had calmed the small sufferer she <lb/>
would dress the wounds. If the child was <lb/>
plainly dying she would tell it in a simple way <lb/>
about Jesus, the children's friend, until the <lb/>
child died peacefully and happily, as did one <lb/>
nine year old girl whose last words were: <lb/>
"When you come to heaven, Sister, I'll meet <lb/>
you at the gates with a bunch of flowers."</p>
<p>Thus, simply, she talked to the children of <lb/>
Christ. Unless for some definite purpose, <lb/>
however, she never talked about her religion <lb/>
to strangers, but when occasion arose she was <lb/>
not afraid to bear witness to her faith. Once, <lb/>
when she was riding in the third class carriage <lb/>
of a train, four or five drunken men got on at <lb/>
one of the way stations. At last Sister Dora <lb/>
<pb n="148"/>
could bear their foul language no longer; rising <lb/>
to her full height&mdash;a commanding figure in her <lb/>
plain black dress and little white bonnet&mdash;she <lb/>
said: "I will not hear the Master whom I <lb/>
serve spoken of in this way." One of them <lb/>
dragged her to her seat and bade her keep still. <lb/>
Having made her protest she wisely saw the <lb/>
folly of any further action. When she got out <lb/>
at her station, however, one of the men came <lb/>
up to her and bade her shake hands for she was <lb/>
"a rare plucky one!"</p>
<p>In this and in many other instances she was <lb/>
"plucky" with the courage that comes from <lb/>
faith. Her creed was that of the Church of <lb/>
England, but she had a broad tolerance for all <lb/>
sects; indeed she often confessed a liking for <lb/>
slightly "sensational" religion. She attended <lb/>
with keen interest a Moody and Sankey revival <lb/>
and afterwards used their hymn book in her <lb/>
hospital. The Oxford Movement, which had <lb/>
stirred all England during her childhood, left <lb/>
her undisturbed. She felt no need of ritual in <lb/>
her worship, and, on the whole, was perhaps a <lb/>
little scornful of it. The Bible was her <reg orig="con-|stant">constant</reg> <lb/>
companion, a marked copy being always <lb/>
with her; a "lady-pupil" who came upon her <lb/>
while she was quietly reading it describes her <lb/>
expression as "unearthly."</p>
<p>And now came the test of Sister Dora's faith. <lb/>
A gentleman connected with the hospital wished <lb/>
to marry her. He was a man of great <reg orig="intellec-|tual">intellectual</reg> <lb/>
power, but lacked one vital possession&mdash; <lb/>
the Christian faith. Although Sister Dora was <lb/>
<pb n="149"/>
attracted to him personally, she felt that it <lb/>
would be wrong for her to marry a professed <lb/>
unbeliever. Mr. Twigg of St. John's, who had <lb/>
helped her before, came to her aid again. <lb/>
There could be but one decision: she put away <lb/>
this earthly love that she might better attain <lb/>
to the heavenly. The strain, however, <reg orig="com-|bined">combined</reg> <lb/>
with her continuous hard work proved <lb/>
almost too much for her. One day she fainted <lb/>
while making up a bed in the ward and for a <lb/>
month was dangerously ill. During this illness <lb/>
perhaps no inquiry was more typical than that <lb/>
of the man nicknamed "Sister's Arm." Each <lb/>
Sunday morning he walked eleven miles to the <lb/>
hospital, pulled the bell with a hard jerk and <lb/>
said to the maid, "How's Sister?" Then he <lb/>
would say, "Tell her that's <hi rend="italic">her</hi> arm that rang <lb/>
the bell," and walk the eleven miles back.</p>
<p>One day, after she had been ill a month, she <lb/>
heard there was to be a serious operation <reg orig="per-|formed">performed</reg> <lb/>
that morning. When the doctors were <lb/>
ready to operate Sister Dora appeared in her <lb/>
old place, and from that time resumed her work <lb/>
with increased vigor. A picture given by one <lb/>
of the "lady-pupils" of the daily hospital <lb/>
routine shows Sister Dora down in the wards <lb/>
at half-past eight in the morning, making beds, <lb/>
giving the patients their breakfast, reading <lb/>
prayers, doing the regular routine of the wards <lb/>
&mdash;"the bright sunshiny way she always worked, <lb/>
with a smile and a pleasant word for everyone, <lb/>
was in itself a medicine of the best kind"&mdash; <lb/>
dressing wounds, caring for the out-patients, <lb/>
<pb n="150"/>
serving the patients' dinner&mdash;which she <reg orig="her-|self">herself</reg> <lb/>
always carved&mdash;prayers again, for the <lb/>
nurses and servants this time, and seeing <reg orig="out-|patients">outpatients</reg> <lb/>
until it was time for the afternoon <lb/>
tea.</p>
<p>As the hospital was small, there was <reg orig="neces-|sarily">necessarily</reg> <lb/>
a large number of out-patients, for only <lb/>
those who could not be treated otherwise were <lb/>
admitted to the wards. One day a woman came <lb/>
in with a gash in her head caused by a drunken <lb/>
husband. As Sister Dora was bandaging it <lb/>
the woman broke out fiercely against her <reg orig="hus-|band">husband</reg>. <lb/>
She would not stand his abuse any <lb/>
longer, she declared. She was going to have <lb/>
him arrested that very day. "Do you really <lb/>
mean it?" asked Sister Dora. "Indeed I do," <lb/>
said her patient. Whereupon Sister Dora took <lb/>
off the bandage she had just put on and bound <lb/>
the broken head up again much more <reg orig="elabo-|rately">elaborately</reg> <lb/>
than before. "Why did you do that?" <lb/>
asked a curious "lady-pupil" later. "Oh," <lb/>
said Sister Dora, her eyes twinkling, "I thought <lb/>
if she did have him arrested the judge would <lb/>
give him another month on account of that <reg orig="sec-|ond">second</reg> <lb/>
bandage." Such incidents as this <reg orig="en-|livened">enlivened</reg> <lb/>
somewhat the rather dreary work of <lb/>
the day.</p>
<p>After the nurses' tea, about half-past five or <lb/>
six was the pleasantest part of the day, for <lb/>
then she talked cheerily to each patient or else <lb/>
someone would play the harmonium and they <lb/>
would all sing hymns. To quote one of the <lb/>
pupils: "Nobody had ever seen such a woman <lb/>
<pb n="151"/>
as this before, so beautiful, so good, so <reg orig="tender-|hearted">tenderhearted</reg>, <lb/>
so strong and so gentle, so full of fun <lb/>
and humor, and of sympathy for broken hearts <lb/>
as well as for every other kind of fracture, and <lb/>
the best friend that many of these poor maimed <lb/>
men had ever known." Then wounds would <lb/>
be dressed for the night, the patients given <lb/>
their supper; after she finished her round of <lb/>
duties she would always read evening prayers <lb/>
for the patients. It did not matter to her that <lb/>
many of them were asleep. In her own words: <lb/>
"The prayers go up for them all the same." <lb/>
This was the record of a day's routine in her <lb/>
hospital&mdash;now truly hers, for in 1874 relations <lb/>
were finally and completely severed between <lb/>
Sister Dora and the Sisterhood of the Good <lb/>
Samaritans. What she said to a friend who <lb/>
was engaging for her a servant for the hospital <lb/>
best expresses her ideal for it: "Tell her this <lb/>
is not an ordinary house, or even hospital; I <lb/>
want her to understand that all who serve here, <lb/>
in whatever capacity, ought to have one rule, <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">love for God</hi>, and then I need not say love for <lb/>
their work. I wish we could use and really <lb/>
mean the word <hi rend="italic">Maison-Dieu."</hi></p>
<p>She was a great believer in prayer and many <lb/>
a man has awakened at night to find her <reg orig="kneel-|ing">kneeling</reg> <lb/>
by his bed quietly praying for him. It has <lb/>
been said of a certain great surgeon who has <lb/>
recently died that before he performed any <lb/>
operation he paused for a moment's prayer. <lb/>
Of Sister Dora it is true that before attending <lb/>
to any wound she first prayed that, through her <lb/>
<pb n="152"/>
as the instrument, God in his loving kindness <lb/>
would effect a cure. She had a great respect <lb/>
for the presence of death, and the doctor's <reg orig="as-|sistants">assistants</reg> <lb/>
no longer smoked and jested at <reg orig="post-|mortem">postmortem</reg> <lb/>
examinations when she was present. <lb/>
On all practical subjects connected with the <lb/>
hospital she brought to bear her great intellect, <lb/>
and to the committees she was the final <reg orig="author-|ity">authority</reg>, <lb/>
and in all contentions, it was Sister Dora, <lb/>
who, calm and clear-sighted, settled the <reg orig="difficul-|ties">difficulties</reg>.</p>
<p>A word must be said of the two missions that <lb/>
were held while she was at Walsall. The first <lb/>
was in 1873. These "missions" of the Church <lb/>
of England are a form of evangelistic "revival <lb/>
meetings." It is a special effort, concentrated <lb/>
through a week or two of powerful appeal, to <lb/>
quicken spiritually those within the church and <lb/>
to bring those outside to a knowledge of the <lb/>
love of God and of his power to save sinners. <lb/>
On the second night of this first mission, Sister <lb/>
Dora went out into the streets to bring in those <lb/>
who would not come by themselves, and entered <lb/>
the church with thirty or forty in her train. <lb/>
The second mission was held in 1876, and she <lb/>
prepared to work for it more earnestly than <lb/>
for the first.</p>
<p>With her as guide, two of the clergy went into <lb/>
the worst parts of Walsall. One night the <lb/>
whole company in a saloon, including fifteen or <lb/>
twenty hardened women, went down on their <lb/>
knees while she prayed aloud for these "<reg orig="broth-|ers">brothers</reg> <lb/>
and sisters." While the mission lasted,<lb/>
<pb n="153"/>
Sister Dora and one clergyman held midnight <lb/>
services in a little hall in the heart of the slums, <lb/>
and even after the mission ended Sister Dora <lb/>
continued its work under her own direction. <lb/>
A short service was held late every Sunday <lb/>
night and she would go out personally into the <lb/>
homes of these dissolute men and women and <lb/>
bring them to the service. In all this there was <lb/>
an element of risk, of positive danger, but a <lb/>
rough, "Shut up, you fool&mdash;it's Sister Dora," <lb/>
was enough to forestall any violence.</p>
<p>The year preceding this last mission had been <lb/>
marked by a second outbreak of smallpox in <lb/>
Walsall. After the last epidemic the city <reg orig="au-|thorities">authorities</reg> <lb/>
built an epidemic hospital on the <reg orig="out-|skirts">outskirts</reg> <lb/>
of the town. The difficulty now was to <lb/>
get the people to go to it. They would rather <lb/>
die at home, they said, and those whose relatives <lb/>
were stricken concealed them. Sister Dora, <lb/>
seeing that the spread of the disease was <reg orig="un-|avoidable">unavoidable</reg> <lb/>
under the circumstances, wrote to the <lb/>
authorities that she would nurse the smallpox <lb/>
patients. Thus the difficulty was overcome, for <lb/>
people knew that where Sister Dora was they <lb/>
could trust their relatives. So she dropped <lb/>
her own work and went to take up that of the <lb/>
epidemic hospital, knowing that she herself <lb/>
might take the disease, and with a firmly-fixed <lb/>
presentiment that she might not return alive.</p>
<p>The only help she could get at this hospital <lb/>
was from an old porter&mdash;who would often get <lb/>
drunk and go off for the night&mdash;and two old <lb/>
women from the workhouse. In a letter she <lb/>
<pb n="154"/>
says: "I came and opened the smallpox <reg orig="hos-|pital">hospital</reg> <lb/>
on Saturday. It was spreading in the <lb/>
town, and no one could be found to come; also <lb/>
the people could not be persuaded to come until <lb/>
they heard I was here. &hellip; [For help], I have <lb/>
got two 'critters' from the workhouse; one is <lb/>
so helpless, I have to do work for her, and the <lb/>
other sits up at nights so can do no more. &hellip; <lb/>
They [the patients] are all so pleased to have <lb/>
me here. I had such a nice Sunday. God's <lb/>
blessing seems very much on the place. I spoke <lb/>
to them. &hellip; Oh, that I had Mr. Twigg's power <lb/>
to help souls! I know you will all pray for <lb/>
me that, living or dying, I may glorify Him. <lb/>
You must not fret for me." Later she writes: <lb/>
"I rejoice that He has permitted one so <reg orig="un-|worthy">unworthy</reg> <lb/>
to work for Him; and oh, if He should <lb/>
think me fit to lay down my life for Him, rejoice, <lb/>
rejoice at so great a privilege. My heart is <lb/>
running over with thankfulness, and as I toil <lb/>
on I seem to hear the still small voice, 'Ye did <lb/>
it unto Me.' &hellip; Oh, don't talk about my life. <lb/>
If you knew it you would be down on your knees <lb/>
crying for mercy for me, a sinner." "I do <lb/>
miss my Sundays. &hellip; If it were not for the <lb/>
thought 'where two or three are gathered <reg orig="to-|gether">together</reg>, <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">there</hi> am I in the midst,' I do not know <lb/>
what I should do. &hellip; I think I may almost say <lb/>
it is a closer walk with God. With the pestilence <lb/>
all around you cannot help living each day as if <lb/>
it were your last. There has come that peace <lb/>
which the world cannot give. If I had a wish, <lb/>
it would be that He would count me worthy to <lb/>
<pb n="155"/>
lay down my life for Him." To her patients at <lb/>
her own hospital she writes, after having <reg orig="re-|membered">remembered</reg> <lb/>
each one personally: "Have you <lb/>
been singing to-day? You must sing <reg orig="particu-|larly">particularly</reg> <lb/>
'Safe in the arms of Jesus,'<ref target="n6.2" n="2">*</ref>
<note id="n6.2" place="foot" n="2"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p>For the account of the origin of this bymn, see Chapter V, page 127.</p></note>
 and think of <lb/>
me. Living or dying, I am His. Oh, my <reg orig="chil-|dren">children</reg>, <lb/>
you all love me for the very little I do <lb/>
for you; but, oh, if you would only think what <lb/>
Jesus has done, and is doing for you, your <lb/>
hearts would soon be full of love for Him, and <lb/>
you would all choose Him for your Master. <lb/>
Now, whilst you are on your beds, read and <lb/>
study His life; see the road He went, and <reg orig="fol-|low">follow</reg> <lb/>
Him. I know you all want to go to heaven, <lb/>
but wishing will not get you there. You <hi rend="italic">must</hi> <lb/>
choose <hi rend="italic">now</hi> in this life; you cannot choose <reg orig="here-|after">hereafter</reg> <lb/>
when you die. That great multitude St. <lb/>
John saw round the throne <hi rend="italic">had</hi> washed their <lb/>
robes and made them white in the blood of the <lb/>
Lamb, which was shed for each one of you. <lb/>
God loves you; I know it, by His letting you get <lb/>
hurt and bringing you to the hospital. 'As <lb/>
many as I <hi rend="italic">love</hi>, I rebuke and <hi rend="italic">chasten</hi>.' Think <lb/>
over these things my dear children. Your <lb/>
mother is thinking of you and praying for you. <lb/>
And if it please God you should never see her <lb/>
again, will you make up your minds to walk in <lb/>
the narrow way, so that we may all meet in the <lb/>
green fields above? May God bring you all <lb/>
safe there is the earnest prayer of your faithful <lb/>
friend, Sister Dora."</p>
<pb n="156"/>
<p>After six months of this steady and confining <lb/>
service, in spite of her presentiment, she <reg orig="re-|turned">returned</reg> <lb/>
to them and resumed her work quietly. <lb/>
Just two months after her return in October, <lb/>
1875, there was an explosion of one of the <reg orig="smelt-|ing">smelting</reg> <lb/>
furnaces. Eleven men fearfully burned by <lb/>
molten metal, were carried to the hospital, which <lb/>
turned out all but its worst cases to make room <lb/>
for them. Night and day, for ten days Sister <lb/>
Dora worked, cutting away the clothing that <lb/>
would adhere to the burnt flesh, bandaging <lb/>
wounds, and giving what little relief was <reg orig="pos-|sible">possible</reg>. <lb/>
Many people came to offer their help <lb/>
but could not endure the terrible sights and <lb/>
odor. This accident gave the hospital its <reg orig="death-|blow&mdash;it">deathblow&mdash;it</reg> <lb/>
had become fatally infected, and the <lb/>
committee finally determined to pull it down <lb/>
and build a larger new one. In the meantime <lb/>
they fitted up a small house in Bridgeman Street <lb/>
as a temporary hospital.</p>
<p>In this temporary hospital during the winter <lb/>
of 1876-7, Sister Dora began to notice in <reg orig="her-|self">herself</reg> <lb/>
a weakness foreign to her perfect health. <lb/>
Always strong, she had been in the habit of <lb/>
picking up her patients or carrying a dead body <lb/>
without particular effort. Although now only <lb/>
with increased effort, she continued her heavy <lb/>
work until the trouble grew so that she was <lb/>
forced to consult a doctor. There, in the <reg orig="doc-|tor's">doctor's</reg> <lb/>
office, she entered the outskirts of the <reg orig="val-|ley">valley</reg> <lb/>
of the shadow. Although she had concealed <lb/>
her illness up to the last possible moment, she <lb/>
<pb n="157"/>
had begun then to feel the inroads of a <reg orig="malig-|nant">malignant</reg> <lb/>
cancer.</p>
<p>All through that winter she worked with a <lb/>
frenzy that brought remonstrances from her <lb/>
friends. In addition to her work in the <reg orig="hos-|pital">hospital</reg>, <lb/>
at night she carried on the evangelism in <lb/>
the slums which she had begun at the time of <lb/>
the second mission. She was enabled "to see <lb/>
the image of God, defiled and darkened though <lb/>
it might be, impressed upon every living soul, to <lb/>
feel her kinship with it, to lay her hand, not <lb/>
upon the defilements and impurity, but through <lb/>
the means of her infinite love and tenderness, <lb/>
upon the one spot yet capable of being healed, <lb/>
thus kindling the faintest spark into a living <lb/>
flame." On Christmas 1877 (her last) she <reg orig="in-|vited">invited</reg> <lb/>
all her old patients to a dinner which she <lb/>
provided. She worked steadily until June when <lb/>
an outbreak of typhoid in the temporary <reg orig="hos-|pital">hospital</reg> <lb/>
caused its closing, and Sister Dora had an <lb/>
unexpected holiday.</p>
<p>As soon as she was able to leave she visited <lb/>
her nieces in the Isle of Man. From there she <lb/>
went to Paris, and in September was in London <lb/>
studying the treatment of wounds under <reg orig="Pro-|fessor">Professor</reg> <lb/>
Lister. All this time she was bearing <lb/>
alone her own rapidly increasing burden. On <lb/>
October 8 she returned to Walsall where the <lb/>
hospital committee, hearing of her serious <reg orig="ill-|ness">illness</reg>, <lb/>
hired a small house for her. Her <reg orig="condi-|tion">condition</reg> <lb/>
was such that her doctor gave her about a <lb/>
fortnight to live, and on October 10 she wrote <lb/>
to a friend: "It is <hi rend="italic">hopeless</hi> (I use that word <lb/>
<pb n="158"/>
merely technically) so they don't tease me with <lb/>
medicines and remedies, and there is no <reg orig="fluctua-|tion">fluctuation</reg> <lb/>
of hopes and fears. I have not a care; it <lb/>
is all sunshine. God has taken away the fear of <lb/>
death, and all sorrow at parting with life."</p>
<p>On November 4, the new hospital was opened <lb/>
"in the name of Sister Dora," a silver key <reg orig="hav-|ing">having</reg> <lb/>
been sent to her by the committee with the <lb/>
request that she give it to the Mayor and "thus <lb/>
empower him to open the new building <hi rend="italic">in her <lb/>
name."</hi> Where to find her successor had been <lb/>
one of her greatest anxieties, and on December <lb/>
6 it was happily removed. Sister Ellen, a <reg orig="com-|plete">complete</reg> <lb/>
stranger to Sister Dora and to Walsall, <lb/>
offered her services for the hospital. Sister <lb/>
Dora realized that here was the right person, <lb/>
and gave herself up to the relief of being waited <lb/>
on by her. Her release came December 24, 1878. <lb/>
When they could do no more for her she bade <lb/>
them leave her, crying, "I have lived alone; let <lb/>
me die alone." And so she died&mdash;alone save <lb/>
for Him in Whose service she had spent her life <lb/>
&mdash;"not grudgingly or of necessity" but <reg orig="cheer-|fully">cheerfully</reg> <lb/>
and willingly.</p>
<p>Her funeral was attended by all Walsall. By <lb/>
a strange coincidence there were at the same <lb/>
time the funerals of four paupers. Their <lb/>
cort&eacute;ges arrived first and filled the little chapel <lb/>
so that Sister Dora's coffin was left on the porch. <lb/>
The church service was read over the five at <lb/>
once&mdash;as one of the nurses said: "Just as <reg orig="Sis-|ter">Sister</reg> <lb/>
Dora would have wished&mdash;not to be divided, <lb/>
even in death, from the poor people she loved <lb/>
<pb n="159"/>
so well." The police were useless to keep the <lb/>
people out of the cemetery, but it was a quiet, <lb/>
reverent crowd that stood, every man with his <lb/>
hat off, while the beautiful service at the grave <lb/>
was read. Rich and poor, clergy and laymen, <lb/>
bishops and the lowest of them she had worked <lb/>
to help, all united in paying to her this last <reg orig="lov-|ing">loving</reg> <lb/>
tribute.</p>
<p>Her personality still colors Walsall. Among <lb/>
all the monuments proposed for her the one that <lb/>
the working people most desired was not the <lb/>
home for convalescents that she herself wanted <lb/>
to establish, but a statue of her, so that she <lb/>
would be tangibly present to their children and <lb/>
their children's children. As one humble <reg orig="work-|man">workman</reg> <lb/>
said: "Why, nobody knows better than I <lb/>
do that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> sha'n't forget her&mdash;no danger of <lb/>
that; but <hi rend="italic">I</hi> want her to be there, so that when <lb/>
strangers come to the place and see her <reg orig="stand-|ing">standing</reg> <lb/>
up, they shall ask us, 'Who's that?' and then <lb/>
we shall say, <hi rend="italic">'Who's</hi> that? Why, that's <hi rend="italic">our</hi> <lb/>
Sister Dora.'"</p>
<p>She stands there now, a beautiful statue, yet <lb/>
not simply a thing of cold stone, but rather a <lb/>
vital personality&mdash;<hi rend="italic">their</hi> Sister Dora.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
