<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="UVA" rend="none"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="none"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOdia SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-dia.ent"> %ISOdia;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-tech.ent"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="UVA" rend="none">
<teiHeader type="migrated">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Reed_Happy Women</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl/></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2009-09-29">September 29, 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<name id="aec6v">Andrew Curley, University of Virginia Library</name>
<resp>corrector</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>Minor corrections to vendor markup.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="t1">
<body id="t1-body">
<div1 type="fly-title" id="d3">
<pb n="117"/>
<head><hi rend="gothic">Sister Dora</hi></head>
<pb/>
<ab type="empty" rend="none"/>
</div1>
<div1 type="part" id="d4">
<pb n="119"/>
<head><hi rend="gothic">Sister Dora</hi></head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">Side</hi> by side with the name of Florence <lb/>
Nightingale stands that of Dorothy <lb/>
Wyndlow Pattison, familiarly and <reg orig="affec-|tionately">affectionately</reg> <lb/>
known as "Sister Dora." She <lb/>
was born in Yorkshire, England, in 1832, <lb/>
and her childhood was much like that of <lb/>
other children not destined for great work <lb/>
and lasting fame.</p>
<p>It is recorded that, in her early youth, <lb/>
she and her sister were given velvet <lb/>
bonnets which they chose to consider ugly. <lb/>
One day when the two children were left <lb/>
alone in the house, Dorothy whispered, <lb/>
"Come, now is our chance!" It was <lb/>
raining hard, and the inclement weather <lb/>
gave the ingenious Dorothy a bright idea. <lb/>
They put on the hated bonnets, opened <lb/>
<pb n="120"/>
the window, and leaned out into the <lb/>
pouring rain. When the velvet was <lb/>
thoroughly saturated, they returned them <lb/>
to the bandboxes. On the following <reg orig="Sun-|day">Sunday</reg>, <lb/>
when invited to get ready for church, <lb/>
Dorothy explained airily that they could <lb/>
not go until they had new bonnets, as the <lb/>
others were quite unpresentable. The <lb/>
excuse was not accepted, nor did the <lb/>
new bonnets materialise, but Dorothy <lb/>
and her sister were forced, all winter <lb/>
long, to wear the despised and injured <lb/>
headgear, in the exact condition in which <lb/>
it was found!</p>
<p>When she was fourteen, Dorothy had a <lb/>
long and dangerous illness from which she <lb/>
did not recover for months. At that <lb/>
time, England was swept by a great popular <lb/>
enthusiasm inspired by Miss Nightingale's <lb/>
wonderful work in the Crimea, and, though <lb/>
far too young, and not strong enough to <lb/>
take even a short journey, Dorothy begged <lb/>
<pb/>
<figure id="f1" rend="page">
<head>Sister Dora</head>
<p>From the statue erected to her memory</p>
</figure>
<pb/>
<pb n="121"/>
unceasingly to be allowed to join Miss <lb/>
Nightingale and help her in her work.</p>
<p>For years after her recovery she <reg orig="per-|sisted">persisted</reg> <lb/>
in her desire to leave home and <lb/>
become a trained nurse. Her father <reg orig="con-|tinually">continually</reg> <lb/>
opposed it, but finally gave in, <lb/>
when she was twenty-five. He refused <lb/>
to make her any allowance beyond what <lb/>
he had always given her for clothing and <lb/>
pin money, so she was obliged to find a way <lb/>
in which to earn the balance.</p>
<p>For three years she lived alone in a <lb/>
small cottage, teaching school and doing <lb/>
all her own housework. The villagers <lb/>
were much astonished to discover that a <lb/>
woman might be a "real lady" and yet soil <lb/>
her hands continually with tasks which <lb/>
seemed degrading.</p>
<p>Finding it impossible to secure <reg orig="other-|wise">otherwise</reg> <lb/>
the longed-for training, she joined <lb/>
a High Church sisterhood at Coatham, <lb/>
called the Sisterhood of the Good <reg orig="Samari-|tans">Samaritans</reg>, <lb/>
<pb n="122"/>
and was henceforth called "Sister <lb/>
Dora."</p>
<p>The training and discipline of the <reg orig="Sister-|hood">Sisterhood</reg> <lb/>
were rigid in the extreme. The idea <lb/>
was to humble pride, and to inculcate <reg orig="sub-|missiveness">submissiveness</reg> <lb/>
and reverence for authority. <lb/>
Sister Dora was one day ordered to make <lb/>
all the beds in the establishment, and, <reg orig="hav-|ing">having</reg> <lb/>
done so, was invited to pull them all <lb/>
to pieces and do it over. She scrubbed <lb/>
floors, and people came in purposely, with <lb/>
mud and ashes, and made the floors dirty <lb/>
again. Then she was ordered to scrub <lb/>
once more. She also cooked, cleaned <lb/>
grates and stoves, built fires, carried out <lb/>
ashes, and washed dishes&mdash;all with dignity <lb/>
and cheerfulness.</p>
<p>She was sent by the Sisterhood, when <lb/>
her novitiate was over, to a small hospital <lb/>
in Walsall. Toward the end of the year, <lb/>
she received orders to leave the <reg orig="hos-|pital">hospital</reg> <lb/>
and take a private case in the <lb/>
<pb n="123"/>
southern part of England. The people <lb/>
of Walsall objected to her leaving and <lb/>
framed a petition to the Sisterhood. At <lb/>
this time, she received word of her father's <lb/>
dangerous illness, and telegraphed to the <lb/>
Mother Superior, asking permission to go <lb/>
to him. This was immediately and sternly <lb/>
refused and she was ordered at once to <lb/>
Devonshire. With aching heart, she went. <lb/>
On reaching her patient's home, she learned <lb/>
that her father was dead. Then the <reg orig="Sister-|hood">Sisterhood</reg>, <lb/>
too late, relaxed its discipline, and <lb/>
wrote to her: "You may attend your <lb/>
father's funeral, if you please." Bitterly, <lb/>
she answered thus: "When my father was <lb/>
alive, you did not permit me to go to him. <lb/>
Now that he is dead, I no longer care to go."</p>
<p>Yet for ten years she continued to be a <lb/>
devoted member of the Sisterhood. She <lb/>
returned to Walsall, and among the poor, <lb/>
the ignorant, and the afflicted, carried the <lb/>
gospel of cleanliness and hope.</p>
<pb n="124"/>
<p>Once, when the impression got abroad <lb/>
that the "Good Samaritans" were papists, <lb/>
the hospital was stoned by a mob from the <lb/>
coal mines. Sister Dora was badly cut <lb/>
on the forehead and carried the scar to <lb/>
her dying day. Before her wound had <lb/>
healed, however, the lad who threw the <lb/>
stone was carried into the hospital, badly <lb/>
hurt. Sister Dora recognised him, and <lb/>
gave him special care. One day, during <lb/>
his convalescence, he confessed, sobbing,<lb/>
"Sister, I threw that stone at you."</p>
<p>"Yes," she answered, quietly, "I know. <lb/>
I knew it as soon as you were brought in <lb/>
here."</p>
<p>"You knew," cried the boy, in wonder <lb/>
and admiration, "and yet you have been <lb/>
taking care of me like this!"</p>
<p>She was once given charge of an old <lb/>
lady who was violently insane, and whom <lb/>
everyone else feared to approach. Sister <lb/>
Dora's gentleness, patience, and tact won <lb/>
<pb n="125"/>
the poor creature's affections, and <reg orig="eventu-|ally">eventually</reg>, <lb/>
through love, the old lady became <lb/>
cured. Long afterward, in speaking of <lb/>
it, Sister Dora said, "I had an uncommonly <lb/>
pleasant time with that mad old lady!"</p>
<p>Loving all deeply and unselfishly, <reg orig="Sis-|ter">Sister</reg> <lb/>
Dora inspired her patients with that <lb/>
answering love through which miracles <lb/>
are wrought. Once, when holding a badly <lb/>
burned child in her arms, Sister Dora <lb/>
whispered, "Hush, don't cry; Sister's <lb/>
got you!" "Oh," sobbed the child, <lb/>
"when you get to heaven, Sister Dora, <lb/>
I'll be waiting at the gate for you with a <lb/>
bouquet of flowers!"</p>
<p>By skilled nursing, she saved a badly <lb/>
injured arm which the surgeons said would <lb/>
have to be amputated. The man ever <lb/>
afterward alluded to it gratefully as "Sister <lb/>
Dora's arm." When she was ill and he <lb/>
had fully recovered, he would walk eleven <lb/>
miles to the hospital every Sunday <reg orig="morn-|ing">morning</reg>, <lb/>
<pb n="126"/>
to ask for her. He never failed to <lb/>
leave this characteristic message: "Tell <lb/>
her it's her arm that rang the bell."</p>
<p>Twice she served through smallpox <reg orig="epi-|demics">epidemics</reg>. <lb/>
At the second one an <reg orig="ambu-|lance">ambulance</reg> <lb/>
was provided in Walsall to take the <lb/>
stricken ones to the hospital. Sister Dora <lb/>
would drive to a house, enter unannounced, <lb/>
and say she had come to take the patient <lb/>
to the hospital. Resistance was useless, <lb/>
for Sister Dora was strong, and more than <lb/>
once she simply took an unwilling patient <lb/>
in her arms, either man or woman, <reg orig="depos-|ited">deposited</reg> <lb/>
her ailing burden in the ambulance, <lb/>
and drove on. It is said that the whole <lb/>
town was cheered and kept from panic <lb/>
by the frequent passing of the ambulance <lb/>
and Sister Dora "with her jolly face smiling <lb/>
out of the window."</p>
<p>For six months she was practically <lb/>
alone in a hospital full of smallpox patients. <lb/>
She never had her bonnet on and went no <lb/>
<pb n="127"/>
farther than the gate, yet, from here, she <lb/>
wrote to a friend: "I am still a prisoner, <lb/>
surrounded by my lepers. I do feel so <lb/>
thankful that I came. I thank God daily <lb/>
for my life here."</p>
<p>Eventually, she left the Sisterhood, and <lb/>
continued her work unhampered by <reg orig="re-|strictions">restrictions</reg>. <lb/>
"I am a woman," she <reg orig="ex-|plained">explained</reg>, <lb/>
"and not a piece of furniture." <lb/>
She renounced marriage with the man she <lb/>
loved that she might continue in her <reg orig="pro-|fession">profession</reg>. <lb/>
"The world needs me more than <lb/>
he does," she said, "and I can never give <lb/>
up my work."</p>
<p>At forty-four, Sister Dora was stricken <lb/>
with an incurable disease. The surgeon <lb/>
whom she consulted told her that an <reg orig="opera-|tion">operation</reg> <lb/>
might prolong her life, but could not <lb/>
save it. She insisted that the fact be kept <lb/>
secret&mdash;and went on with her work.</p>
<p>Knowing that her days were numbered, <lb/>
she was eager to crowd in as much of life <lb/>
<pb n="128"/>
as possible. She went to London to study <lb/>
a new antisepticising process; she went to <lb/>
the Paris Exposition to see new surgical <lb/>
appliances. Incredible as it may seem, <lb/>
she became more sunny and cheerful than <lb/>
ever. She was more self-sacrificing in <lb/>
behalf of her patients, more sternly <reg orig="self-|denying">self-denying</reg>, <lb/>
more Christ-like, and even <reg orig="hap-|pier">happier</reg> <lb/>
than she had ever been before.</p>
<p>When she returned to Walsall, a new <lb/>
hospital bearing her name was opened <lb/>
by the Mayor, but she was too ill to be <lb/>
present. The townspeople refused to <reg orig="be-|lieve">believe</reg> <lb/>
that their "dear lady" was ill, and <lb/>
when at last they were convinced that <lb/>
she could not recover, everyone was <reg orig="grief-|stricken">grief-stricken</reg>.</p>
<p>In every church, twice on Sundays and <lb/>
at the Wednesday night prayer-meeting, <lb/>
public prayers were offered for Sister Dora's <lb/>
restoration to health. In October, 1878, <lb/>
she wrote to a friend: "The decree has <lb/>
<pb n="129"/>
gone forth, 'Sister, put thy house in order, <lb/>
for thou shalt die, and not live.' There <lb/>
is only Mount Calvary to climb, by the <lb/>
ladder of sickness. I have not had two <lb/>
hours' sleep for four days and nights, but <lb/>
in the midst of the fiery furnace there was a <lb/>
form like unto the Son of God."</p>
<p>Eleven weeks of anguish followed, which <lb/>
she bore heroically, until the end came, on <lb/>
Christmas Eve. "I see Him there," she <lb/>
said; "the gates are opened wide." And <lb/>
through the open gates she went, free at <lb/>
last of all disease and pain, perhaps to <lb/>
find the poor little burned child of so many <lb/>
years ago, who had promised to wait at <lb/>
the gate for her "with a bouquet of <lb/>
flowers."</p>
<p>It was a sad Christmas Day for Walsall, <lb/>
and no celebrations were held. In some <lb/>
cases, even the presents intended for the <lb/>
children were put away, sadly, by weeping <lb/>
men and women. The whole city, <reg orig="wor-|shipping">worshipping</reg> <lb/>
<pb n="130"/>
her while living, paid honour to <lb/>
her when she was dead.</p>
<p>Eight years afterward, in the midst of the <lb/>
smoke and dirt of the central part of <reg orig="Wal-|sall">Walsall</reg>, <lb/>
was erected a noble statue, of purest <lb/>
marble&mdash;a likeness of Sister Dora when she <lb/>
was young and beautiful, strong, and <lb/>
happy in her chosen work. In her last <lb/>
days she said once that she wished she <lb/>
had married, but otherwise she voiced no <lb/>
regret, even for her intense bodily pain. <lb/>
"Say of me," she said, "only this&mdash;she <lb/>
hath done what she could!"</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
