<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="UVA" rend="none"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="none"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOdia SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-dia.ent"> %ISOdia;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-tech.ent"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="UVA" rend="none">
<teiHeader type="migrated">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Wilmot-Buxton_Book of Noble Women</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl/></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2009-09-29">September 29, 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<name id="aec6v">Andrew Curley, University of Virginia Library</name>
<resp>corrector</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>Minor corrections to vendor markup.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="t1">
<body id="t1-body">
<div1 type="part" id="d3">
<pb/>
<figure id="f1" rend="page">
<p>SISTER DORA</p>
</figure>
</div1>
<div1 type="part" id="d4">
<pb n="275"/>
<head>A SISTER DORA <lb/>
(DOROTHY WINSLOW PATTISON)</head>
<epigraph>
<cit>
<q>"Her Angel's face <lb/>
As the great eye of Heaven shyned bright <lb/>
And made a sunshine in the shady place."</q>
<bibl><author><hi rend="small-caps">Spenser,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Faery Queene</hi></author></bibl>
</cit>
</epigraph>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">No</hi> place in the world perhaps needs sunshine&mdash;<lb/>
moral as well as actual sunshine&mdash;as the <lb/>
wards of a hospital.</p>
<p>It is hard, too, for the sun to shine in Walsall, <lb/>
because of the pall of smoke that hangs over the <lb/>
town, with its many chimneys and great iron <lb/>
foundries. The inhabitants of the place are not <lb/>
of the most refined order, yet the roughest of <lb/>
the rough iron-workers had a smile and a nod <lb/>
for the bright-faced woman in nurse's uniform as she <lb/>
passed amongst them.</p>
<p>For it was she who had brought the sunshine <lb/>
of human sympathy and tenderness to them, or <lb/>
to their relatives who had suffered in disease <lb/>
or accident&mdash;suffered often despairingly, till she <lb/>
had brought to them the gift of hope. And if <lb/>
you asked any of those grimy fellows who it <lb/>
was who had passed by, they would reply, in <lb/>
surprise at your ignorance&mdash;</p>
<pb n="276"/>
<p>"Who is it? Why, it's <hi rend="italic">our</hi> Sister Dora!"</p>
<p>In the year 1832 Dora Pattison was born in <lb/>
the little Yorkshire village of Hauxwell, in the <lb/>
North Riding of Yorkshire, of which her father <lb/>
was the rector. Her childhood was marked by a <lb/>
quiet but persistent determination to get her <lb/>
own way by one device or another, which <lb/>
already spoke of the strong will and firm <lb/>
purpose of the future woman. In these early <lb/>
days, however, it was occasionally doomed to <lb/>
failure. She tells an amusing story of some <lb/>
hated velvet bonnets which she and her sister <lb/>
were obliged to wear on Sundays. Dora was <lb/>
determined firmly to avoid appearing in them; <lb/>
so she waited for a soaking wet day, and only <lb/>
delaying long enough to make sure her mother <lb/>
had gone for a drive, rushed upstairs and said <lb/>
to her sister, "Be quick: now's our chance for <lb/>
spoiling our bonnets!"</p>
<p>Hastily they put them on, opened the library <lb/>
windows and stuck their heads well out, until <lb/>
the velvet was drenched through and through. <lb/>
When the soaking was complete, the offensive <lb/>
headgear was put away again. Sunday came, <lb/>
and their mother, seeing them bareheaded, inquired, <lb/>
"Where are your bonnets?"</p>
<p>"Quite spoilt," replied Dora firmly; "we can <lb/>
never wear them again."</p>
<p>Mrs Pattison thought differently, however; they <lb/>
were made to wear them for many a long week, and the <lb/>
naughty little girls were obliged to confess that they <lb/>
had not improved matters by their skilful man&oelig;uvre.</p>
<pb n="277"/>
<p>The healthy, open life of the moors changed <lb/>
Dora from a delicate child to a strong, bonny, merry <lb/>
girl, full of a vigour which became restlessness as <lb/>
soon as her energy failed to find sufficient scope. <lb/>
She was intensely eager to join Miss Nightingale's <lb/>
band of nurses for the Crimea; but her father, <lb/>
realising her want of training and discipline, told <lb/>
her, quite rightly, that she would be worse than <lb/>
useless, and refused to let her go. She chafed <lb/>
inwardly, but outwardly submitted for a time to <lb/>
the quiet home-life, of which her bright face <lb/>
and never failing spirits made her the "Sunshine" <lb/>
that her father always called her. Then her <lb/>
mother died, and a new fit of restless energy took <lb/>
possession of the girl.</p>
<p>Nothing would content her but a life of hard <lb/>
work and poverty; and so she became a village <lb/>
schoolmistress, where she obtained all she could <lb/>
want of both. She loved the children and managed <lb/>
them excellently, but her vocation did not lie in <lb/>
the direction of teaching. The loneliness of the <lb/>
country cottage oppressed her spirits; she <reg orig="con-|stantly">constantly</reg> <lb/>
wished to be elsewhere. Suddenly she <lb/>
made up her mind that if she could but go into <lb/>
a Sisterhood all would be well&mdash;that the giving up <lb/>
of that strong will of hers would lead to perfect <lb/>
peace. A severe illness forced her to resign her <lb/>
school-work, and she barely allowed herself time <lb/>
to get well before attaching herself in her usual <lb/>
headstrong haste to a working Sisterhood at <lb/>
Coatham, in Yorkshire.</p>
<p>It was not in the least likely that such a <lb/>
<pb n="278"/>
restricted life would suit her. She was of too <lb/>
strong a nature to mould her character according <lb/>
to the bidding of others, too fond of her own <lb/>
way to ever really give up her will, and had too <lb/>
masculine a force of both mind and body ever <lb/>
to settle down happily in a community of women. <lb/>
But it was a period of excellent discipline for her. <lb/>
Cleaning hearths, making beds, or scrubbing floors <lb/>
is no bad outlet for superfluous energy, though <lb/>
she was very thankful when the opening of a <lb/>
little cottage hospital at Walsall gave her more <lb/>
congenial work.</p>
<p>At first Sister Dora, as she was henceforth to be <lb/>
called, was the merest subordinate, as became her <reg orig="posi-|tion">position</reg> <lb/>
as a novice almost entirely ignorant of nursing.</p>
<p>Most of the cases brought to the hospital were <lb/>
surgical, the result of the ghastly accidents which <lb/>
were always occurring in the coal and iron <lb/>
pits; and so expert did she soon become in <lb/>
tending these that when a sudden order from <lb/>
the Coatham Sisterhood bade her go at once and <lb/>
nurse a private case in Devonshire, both the <lb/>
hospital committee and she herself were inclined <lb/>
to rebel. Just at that moment a letter reached <lb/>
her with the news that her father was dying, and <lb/>
earnestly wished to see her. She telegraphed <lb/>
to Coatham for leave to go to him at once; but, <lb/>
possibly with the idea that she needed to be <lb/>
taught the lesson of obedience and self-denial, this <lb/>
was refused. With a heavy heart, she set off for <lb/>
Devonshire, and had only just arrived when she <lb/>
heard of her father's death.</p>
<pb n="279"/>
<p>She returned at once to Walsall, wretched and <lb/>
deeply depressed in mind and body. Henceforth <lb/>
her connection with the Sisterhood was much <lb/>
weakened, except in so far as she wished to carry <lb/>
on the work she had begun with them. A few <lb/>
years later she parted from it altogether; but <lb/>
long before this time her real vocation had made <lb/>
itself clear.</p>
<p>The cottage hospital no longer sufficed for its <lb/>
patients' needs, and when a new building was <lb/>
raised on the top of the "Mount," a hill <reg orig="over-|looking">overlooking</reg> <lb/>
the town, its sole management was put <lb/>
into the hands of Sister Dora. Scarcely was it <lb/>
opened when smallpox broke out in Walsall, and <lb/>
although infectious cases were not admitted, the <lb/>
brave woman, arguing that she was exposed to <lb/>
infection anyhow from the many surgical <reg orig="out-|patients">outpatients</reg> <lb/>
who came to her with the disease upon <lb/>
them, gave up the time that should have been <lb/>
devoted to sleep or rest, to nursing in their own <lb/>
homes those who otherwise would have been entirely <lb/>
neglected.</p>
<p>She was called one night to the bedside of one <lb/>
of her old patients, who was dying of the disease <lb/>
in its most malignant form. He was quite alone <lb/>
in a miserable room lit by one small bit of <reg orig="candle-|end">candle-end</reg>. <lb/>
Calling a neighbour, Sister Dora gave her <lb/>
money to buy some means of light, while she <lb/>
remained with the sufferer. The woman never <lb/>
returned, and so she sat in the gathering darkness <lb/>
alone with the dying man. Just as the candle <lb/>
was sputtering out, he rose in bed, exclaiming, <lb/>
<pb n="280"/>
"Sister, kiss me before I die." She took him in <lb/>
her arms and kissed the poor disfigured face, <lb/>
promising she would never leave him while he <lb/>
lived. And then began the awful watching, in <lb/>
complete darkness, for the death which she did not <lb/>
recognise even when it came. For when, at the <lb/>
first glimmer of dawn, she went to seek his <lb/>
neighbours, the man had been dead some <lb/>
hours.</p>
<p>Her chief interest lay, however, in trying to save <lb/>
the limbs of those who had been mutilated by the <lb/>
machinery of the iron pits. One of these cases was <lb/>
especially touching. A fine strong young collier <lb/>
was brought in with a terribly mangled arm. <lb/>
"Nothing can save it; amputation must take place <lb/>
at once," pronounced the surgeon. The answering <lb/>
groan of despair from the patient called up on the <lb/>
nurse's face a look of such deep pity that the man <lb/>
exclaimed, "Oh, Sister, save my arm for me! It's <lb/>
my right arm."</p>
<p>Turning to the doctor, she said, "I believe I can <lb/>
save this arm, if you will let me try."</p>
<p>The doctor was naturally extremely angry, and <lb/>
told her roughly that he knew best, and that if the <lb/>
arm were not amputated at once, the man would die.</p>
<p>The patient listened eagerly to the altercation; <lb/>
but when the choice was given him, he gladly <lb/>
consented to take his chance with Sister <lb/>
Dora.</p>
<p>"Very well," said the irate surgeon; "but <lb/>
remember it's <hi rend="italic">your</hi> arm&mdash;you take the responsibility. <lb/>
I will have nothing to do with the case."</p>
<pb n="281"/>
<p>So she was left to do as best she could. "How <lb/>
I prayed over that arm!" she used to say in later <lb/>
days, when she described the almost ceaseless <reg orig="tend-|ing">tending</reg> <lb/>
given to it for three weeks. At the end of that time, <lb/>
she called the doctor to inspect her work. "Why, <lb/>
you have saved it!" he cried, and with generous <lb/>
triumph brought in the whole of the hospital staff <lb/>
to show them "what could be done in the way of <lb/>
conservative surgery," as he called it.</p>
<p>Some time after her patient had left the hospital, <lb/>
Sister Dora had a severe illness, brought on by <reg orig="over-|work">overwork</reg> <lb/>
and worry. All through this anxious period this <lb/>
young man walked eleven miles into Walsall every <lb/>
Sunday, his only holiday, and giving a vigorous pull <lb/>
at the bell, would ask, "How's Sister?" And when <lb/>
he had been answered, he would say, "Tell her that's <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">her</hi> arm what rang the bell," and then turned to <lb/>
walk his weary journey back again.</p>
<p>Her influence over men was wonderful, and a <lb/>
sojourn in her hospital ward often sent a man out <lb/>
a reformed character. Her delightful humour was <lb/>
partly the secret of this influence. "Make you <lb/>
laugh?" said a burly Irishman. "She'd make you <lb/>
laugh if you were dying!"</p>
<p>"My dear," she would sometimes say, "if I could <lb/>
not laugh over the things, I don't know what I <lb/>
should do."</p>
<p>Her powers of endurance were even more <reg orig="mar-|vellous">marvellous</reg>. <lb/>
From the time she rose in the morning <lb/>
till the last thing at night she was incessantly at <lb/>
work; and the bell which hung over her bed, and <lb/>
communicated with the patients' ward, was seldom <lb/>
<pb n="282"/>
still at night. Perhaps she erred on the side <lb/>
of thinking that no one could ever take her place or <lb/>
relieve her of any of her duties because of their <lb/>
comparative inefficiency; certainly her patients <lb/>
considered themselves ill-used if they were tended <lb/>
by any hands save hers.</p>
<p>In 1875 a fresh and terrible outbreak of <reg orig="small-|pox">smallpox</reg> <lb/>
occurred in Walsall. An epidemic hospital <lb/>
had been built on the outskirts of the town, but no <lb/>
power could induce the poor people to send their <lb/>
infected relations thither, and so stay the spread of <lb/>
the disease. At this crisis Sister Dora suddenly <lb/>
offered to leave her own work and go to nurse the <lb/>
patients in the smallpox hospital. The authorities <lb/>
eagerly seized the chance. Others might manage <lb/>
the accidents; only Sister Dora could induce the <lb/>
Walsall folk to send their smallpox cases to be <lb/>
under her care.</p>
<p>The offer was not made lightly; for Sister Dora <lb/>
was one of those who catch every disease to which <lb/>
they are exposed, and she went, moreover, with a <lb/>
depressing conviction that she should never return <lb/>
to her beloved accident wards. Yet she only <lb/>
flinched once from what she considered a plain <lb/>
duty, and that was when she found herself on the <lb/>
doorstep of the incredibly dismal building, standing <lb/>
in the midst of heaps of "slag," with a few blackened <lb/>
cabbages growing at its entrance.</p>
<p>Shivering with irrepressible dread at the thought <lb/>
of a lonely struggle with the most loathsome form <lb/>
of disease, she said to the surgeon who had brought <lb/>
her, "Oh, take me back! I can't endure this <reg orig="dread-|ful">dreadful</reg> <lb/>
<pb n="283"/>
place&mdash;I did not know what it would be like!" <lb/>
His only reply was "Come in!"&mdash;and from the <lb/>
moment she crossed the threshold the victory was <lb/>
won.</p>
<p>Nothing but the strongest religious faith could <lb/>
have kept her up in the long battle with disease. <lb/>
She was quite alone save for two old women who <lb/>
came in occasionally from the workhouse to help <lb/>
with the washing, and a night porter who often <lb/>
stayed away and got drunk. Sometimes the delirious <lb/>
patients tried to escape, and she had a hard fight <lb/>
to keep them in bed. All this terrible time she had <lb/>
scarcely any rest, but read the most exciting novels <lb/>
she could get at night to prevent herself becoming <lb/>
too sleepy. When those who were attacked in their <lb/>
own homes refused to come to the hospital, the <lb/>
Sister would go and fetch them herself, lifting them <lb/>
in her arms to the ambulance as though they had <lb/>
been babies instead of grown men and women. <lb/>
Yet she could write, "I thank God daily for my life <lb/>
here. I feel He sent me, and He has blessed it to <lb/>
my own soul." And so that six months of incessant <lb/>
toil amid loathsome surroundings came to an end, <lb/>
and she returned with joy to her own beloved <lb/>
hospital.</p>
<p>Suddenly, in the midst of all her splendid work, <lb/>
the call came to lay it aside. A terrible internal <lb/>
disease manifested itself, but true to all her <reg orig="self-|denying">self-denying</reg> <lb/>
instincts Sister Dora kept the fact a <lb/>
complete secret, and went on working harder than <lb/>
ever. Then a period of enforced holiday occurred, <lb/>
while a new and improved hospital was being made <lb/>
<pb n="284"/>
ready for her patients. She visited Paris and <lb/>
London, intent on studying the latest surgical <lb/>
appliances, but these she was never destined <lb/>
to use. Her disease made rapid progress, and <lb/>
her one cry now was, "Let me die among my own <lb/>
people!"</p>
<p>So she returned to Walsall, to a little house <lb/>
near the unfinished hospital; but the news of her <lb/>
severe illness was received by her "children" <lb/>
&mdash;rough miners and factory workers&mdash;with utter <lb/>
incredulity. Her wonderful strength and vitality <lb/>
had become a matter of course to them. "Her'll <lb/>
get well," they said; "her <hi rend="italic">never</hi> can be going to <lb/>
die."</p>
<p>But when they at length understood, despair <lb/>
reigned in all the slums and byways of Walsall. <lb/>
It was given her to see the new hospital opened, "in <lb/>
the name of Sister Dora"; but the end was <reg orig="draw-|ing">drawing</reg> <lb/>
very near. For a time she was haunted by a <lb/>
horror of that "Brother Death" whose approach <lb/>
had become so familiar to her in the case of others, <lb/>
but this at length passed quite away.</p>
<p>Years before, a little girl of nine years old, too <lb/>
badly burnt to live, had been laid in the nurse's <lb/>
arms. Nothing could be done for her, but Sister <lb/>
Dora never ceased to soothe and comfort the dying <lb/>
child until the end. The little one died quite <lb/>
happily, saying very simply, as she put up her <lb/>
mouth to be kissed, "When you come to heaven, <lb/>
Sister, I'll meet you at the gates with a bunch of <lb/>
flowers."</p>
<p>We can but believe that Sister Dora's last hour, <lb/>
<pb n="285"/>
in the loneliness of death, was cheered by the <lb/>
remembrance of those many souls whom she had <lb/>
tended during their last moments and helped to face <lb/>
death with courage, and who now would throng to <lb/>
meet their "own Sister" on the other side of the <lb/>
grave.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
